Hello, everybody. Welcome to a new episode of the Decent. I'm your host, Ricardo
Loops. And today I'm joined by Doctor Lydia Moland.
She's a professor of Philosophy at Colby College in Waterville Maine in the US.
She has written extensively on 19th century German philosophy.
And more recently, she has also been interested in abolitionism in the US.
And she wrote a book titled Lydia Maria Child, a Radical American Life based on
the American evolutionist with the same name.
So, Doctor Moland, welcome to the show. It's a big pleasure to everyone.
Thank you.
It's a pleasure to be invited and I'm looking forward to our conversation.
OK.
So,
uh I would like to start by talking
about your work on 19th century German philosophy.
So, first of all,
why did you get interested specifically in 19th century German philosophy?
And do you think that if anything, there's
uh specific aspects of it that make it distinct from
other kinds of philosophy, from other places and other time periods?
Yes. Thank you for that.
Um I got interested in German 19th century philosophy through Spinoza.
So I took a very general philosophy course as an undergraduate.
Uh and I had intended to be a political science major,
but I read Spinoza and it just blew my mind and I,
I was so
moved by the vision that Spinoza had of holism and of um and,
and the way he argued that I decided to do more philosophy and ended up
in a course that ended with
Kant.
And I think as many people do
finished with some very deep dissatisfactions with
Kant's dualism and with his rationalism.
And someone said to me, well, if you are impatient with Kant,
maybe you should try Hegel.
Uh So the next semester,
I took a course on the Phenomenology of Spirit and then I was just hooked.
Um and I
ended up going to Tubingen in Germany where Hegel himself studied,
I lived there for a couple of years and really immersed myself in the
culture of that particular time period. So
many of your viewers will know that Tubing in is
also where Holderlin lived and studied and also shelling.
So Hagel was there in this incredibly fertile environment where
people were taking
very seriously.
Spinoza
was still essentially forbidden.
He was still considered too controversial and too heretical to take seriously.
But they were all
sort of closet spin assists.
And um I, I found all of that very intriguing. I think what,
what really pulled me into Hagel was
his attempt to make philosophical sense of religion
and of protestantism.
In particularly I came from a protestant background and was really intrigued by
his attempt to show what was
important and
vital about the protestant worldview without attaching it
to a kind of uh religious literalism.
Um So that was, that was very helpful to me,
even just in thinking through my own philosophical questions.
So as far as what makes that period distinct, um
a couple of things come to mind, again, sort of connected to Spinoza. I think
the, again, this idea of holism, the attempt not to
think of philosophy as just addressing one problem or
focusing on just epistemology or just in the physics.
But
the idea that an idea could possibly explain
kind of everything.
Um
I think characterizes a lot of early 19th century philosophy in Germany,
certainly not later.
But
sometimes when I teach students this,
I find that, that,
that claim is really strange to them that there could
be one answer or one idea that could explain everything.
But I sometimes push back on that and say,
wouldn't it be even stranger
if different parts of the reality or of
philosophy were totally unconnected from each other?
I wouldn't it be sort of strange if
nature functions in a completely different way from art
or from politics or from epistemology? So,
isn't there something even just more intellectually consistent about looking for
an idea that could explain most of
human experience and maybe even nonhuman experience?
So that's one
another, I think a lot of really existential
questions get started in the 19th century. So you see that some in Kant for sure.
But I think it took this
generation of thinkers who grew up in the French revolution,
which meant that everything they thought they knew about the way politics could
and should work
were um was, was challenged.
And then there were great hopes around the French revolution
and then they were dashed. And so this was a generation that really grew up
feeling the existential weight of a major historical
disappointment if you were a young person in that
generation.
Um And, and so the combination I think of K
turn towards the subject,
which really gives an individual subject an enormous amount of power.
And therefore, also responsibility
opens up these big existential questions and then living in
this part of history where there are enormous shifts um
that ask questions like what is the role of politics
and what is the role of the individual in politics?
And how do individuals
assert themselves in the face of great historical forces?
Um Those set the stage for the kinds of grappling with,
what does it mean to be an individual? What does it mean to be alienated in a society?
Um Obviously something that's been picked up by
Marx and then more by Kirkegaard and Nietzsche
later in the century.
Um And then I would also say, and, and this is clearly in part because of my own work,
a real reorientation around art
and around aesthetic experience.
So that certainly gets started in Kant with his taking
seriously aesthetic experience is one of the most important things about
human experience.
Um But then when you get to people like Hegel,
but also very much his contemporaries like
Lael
or Novalis,
Bettina von Ar
Carlina Von Gunder
Rode.
Um some of these other people who saw in
art and then also in nature and our aesthetic responses to nature,
really central truths about
the human condition.
Then I,
I think you get something very interesting that lasts throughout the century
in part because I think one way I try to think about it is
the question, what if art far from being derivative or entertaining
or the thing that we can philosophize about
kind of if we get to it?
What if instead it is the thing,
the thing that that can explain
us to ourselves and the world to
ourselves better than other branches of philosophy.
If that's true,
then a lot of things need to be revolved um sort in any kind of revolution
so that I'll stop there.
But those are a couple of the things that I find really compelling and possibly
um I don't know, unique but certainly
indicative of that period in that place in the world.
OK.
So I have to tell you straight away that the three
German philosophers whose work I'm most familiar with are Kent Nietzsche
and Schopenhauer. So
uh probably because of some of my personality traits.
I don't know exactly why, but those are the three I felt most
compelled about.
And, uh, I mean, but, uh, of course,
I guess that
we could pretty much say that, uh, everyone in the 19th century in German was
to some extent influenced by Kent. Right?
I mean, even the ones who rejected most of his philosophy or some,
or parts of his philosophy, like for example,
Schopenhauer and Nietzsche,
Nietzsche,
to a greater extent, even them were very, very much influenced by Kent. I,
I think we could
and of course, uh I mean, it's not that German philosophy in the 19th centuries
is a monolith, like for example, sometimes people talk about German idealism,
but I mean, you get into figures like
Schopenhauer and Nietzsche
and they were extremely different from
can or what you would consider just
general idealism. Nietzsche
particularly sometimes is classified as a
romantic or rationalist and he certainly rejected
many
aspects
of Kent's philosophy. And
Schopenhauer was very much a pessimist for example. So,
uh but I mean, do you think that we could look uh even with those differences?
And of course, we could talk about the other philosophers and they certainly have
m many distinct things about their philosophical corpus, I think. But
uh do you think that e even with all of those differences
and existentialism also that I didn't mention and all of that,
that we can still find recurrent themes in 19th century German philosophy.
Yeah, I mean, I,
I think one really is the struggle with the nature of subjectivity and what it means.
Epistemological, metaphysically, politically, aesthetically.
Uh What does it mean
to be a self?
And like if you think not to oversimplify,
but if you think about someone like Descartes just saying, well,
the self is a thinking thing.
It's essentially an immaterial substance.
Um its essence is just to think and it subsists as a thinking thing.
Um
You know, a quick contrast to Kant, I think is
Kant's idea of this self as an activity.
So as something that is actively synthesizing whatever is coming at it
and that it only achieves selfhood through
being active.
And I think
in a way, one of the questions that survives all the way through the century then is
um what kind of activity is that?
And what does the basis of thinking through subjectivity?
Um mean for objectivity
and for reality and for how we treat other people
and obviously paired with that is the
question of whether there is a transcendent divine
that humans are beholden to or created by
and who
dictates reality as we see it. And in my opinion, Hagel, for instance,
is trying very hard to reorient us from that
to seeing that humans are the only creators of meaning
and that we only create meaning
in
cooper operation with each other.
So there's,
if you think about kind as primarily thinking of the subject as activity.
Hagel,
I think picks that up but with a
much stronger emphasis on the kind of mutual recognition
that's necessary
to think about
my being a subject is dependent on your recognizing me as a subject.
And only when we recognize each other, not just abs as abstract subjects,
but as subjects embodied in different roles and different
areas of history, different life plans.
Can we really treat each other with the dignity and respect
that Kant had originally said we owed each other.
And so I think like if you follow that trajectory out um and start to think about like
Kirke
guards grappling with what it meant
to be a subject kind of at odds with
um
with the conventional world or norms that were
established by a society that he didn't feel
um
acknowledged by. And then someone like Nietzsche,
who I think is even more
expressly celebrating
the agony and the ecstasy of being a self creating subject.
So I think in, in Nietzsche
much more than in Hegel,
you get again the existential.
Yeah, I'll say it again,
agony and ecstasy of the fact that we have to create
our own meaning where we can't rely on the divine or on
nature as something separate from us to tell us what is meaningful,
we have to do it ourselves.
And that
um is a great privilege and honor,
but also an enormous responsibility that I think in Nietzsche's
view more than in Hagel's only some people are really up to shouldering.
So in, in each of them,
you get the sense that lots of people would just really
rather prefer to have others tell them what is meaningful.
Um And our calling is to resist that.
I think Hagel, for instance, is much less interested in that kind of resistance
and more interested in trying to think of
ourselves as a cooperating group of people,
each with our own subjectivities.
But working out our subjectivity and our bid for
freedom very much with each other as opposed to
in the kind of individualistic way that you get
with Nietzsche.
That subjectivity part.
I mean, what I'm going to say now,
if I say something that you don't agree with or you think is incorrect,
please correct me.
But
uh I mean, of course, in someone like Nietzsche
and is
to some extent, perspect perspective is philosophy because he,
he particularly in beyond good and evil, for example.
And when and when it comes to morality more specifically,
there, there are places in his work where he expresses a very
uh perspective
perspective on,
on things uh uh and things seem to be very dependent on the subject and subjectivity.
But
uh I mean, uh don't you think that even in Kent, particularly when
uh in the critic of purism, he talks about, for example,
the limits
of, of our
uh
o of the information we can get from our senses, the
uh th those kinds of limits and,
and also the fact that we uh sort of uh have some sort of categories of understanding.
And I think that some of them,
they, it takes from,
I guess Aristotle, if I'm not mistaken and
expands on them, I mean,
the a and then the, and then also when he gets into the, the
antinomy and he talks about
the things that even
as through a reasoning process cannot fully answer.
Like for example, if there's life after death, if there's a God,
if the universe is infinite in time and space questions like that.
Uh I, I mean, that isn't there,
even if only a tiny seed of subjectivity planted there because
I mean,
it seems that there's the thing in itself or whatever reality is
and then our own limitations as human subjects when it comes to
perceiving it and getting
an objective understanding
of what it is. I, I mean, I, I don't know, what are your thoughts on this?
Yeah, absolutely. I think that's 100% right? And I think
that's a
kind of radical
postulate that I don't even think
Kant felt the existential weight of
which is to say
it took someone.
Well, I, I, I'm much more familiar with the early romantics, you know, the
Schlegel and,
and Schelling and, and Novalis and Gunter
Rode
and people like that
who took that.
I, I just feel like much more to heart and as you say,
I think it is partly dispositional or generational
that, you know, can have laid those things out fairly matter of factly.
But I think that the consequences for how we think about our role in,
on our responsibility in the world and the radical perspect
nature of that, as you say, um
was really exhilarating and upsetting to
more to the next generation of thinkers.
So getting into Hegel
and specifically, of course, you've already said a few things about him, but
getting specifically to into aesthetics because when we think about Hegel,
I mean, people who are not philosophers and not specifically very familiar with
Hegel's philosophy,
we tend to just think about his more
systematic and abstract approaches to history and uh
uh thesis,
antithesis
synthesis and stuff like that.
But he also in fact wrote about aesthetics.
Yes. And that was part of his system for sure.
So um aesthetics is the first part of absolute spirit.
So if you think of, of, you know, the system writ large, you've got
um you know,
subjective spirit and the first you have logic and then you
have philosophy of nature and then in philosophy of spirit,
you first have subjective spirit and then
objective spirit and then absolute spirit.
Absolute spirit is where Hagel talks about the three ways that
he thinks humans grapple with what it means to be human.
So the ways in which we reflect on
um
on the world, but also on our role in the world.
So the first of those is art and then religion and then
being a philosopher, Hagel always has philosophy win at the end.
So philosophy for Hagel is still
the best
um most complete and most explicit way that humans
reckon with their um their own status and ask themselves
about meaning in the world.
But art has a really important place in that
for Hagel because we are embodied sensual beings.
And contrary to what some people think about Hagel,
he doesn't regret that.
I mean, it isn't that if we could, we should get rid of that part of ourselves.
I think he thinks that that's a very rich and very vital
way in which humans remain part of the natural world. So we continue to
feel and smell and hear things um that are outside of us. But
we also use our senses to create things that then mean something to us
and that reflect our own grappling with that meaning.
So
I think that for Hegel, aesthetics
is
the sensuous way of experiencing truth.
So truth for Hegel again, back to Spinoza is this very holistic view of
the identity of identity and difference.
So he says the true is the whole,
it's the thing that brings together contraries
and this is where people get the thesis
sis synthesis um
theme that you just referred to.
And so art is the way that we can
sense that truth through our senses as opposed to
understanding it through narratives, which is the way
Hegel characterizes religion. So
interestingly,
religion for him is primarily about narrative
stories that we tell ourselves to explain
everything from the origin of the world to
um you know, our own relationship to each other through.
And then philosophy is supposed to do
that without narrative and without our senses.
So just through thought.
So then within aesthetics, Hagel's
project is to say
how art does that
and which kinds of art and which particular instances of art do that best?
So for him, the question always is,
is this particular art form or this particular artwork allowing us to sense
the idea
which is the unity of unity and division or the true? That is the whole.
So he does this um in a couple of ways.
Um One by giving what some people call
the first really philosophical history of art.
I always think people are too quick to assign
first to anything and usually when they do that,
it's to a male European philosopher.
And I think that is often not true. So I try to be
skeptical about that.
Um but whether he was first or not,
he certainly had a very influential idea of the sort of history and progress of art.
So that's in what's part two of his lectures
on the philosophy of art.
And then he has a whole part three and I'm happy to get into it. This is one of my
major claims in my book on Hagel's aesthetics is that
part three has been essentially neglected by HGL scholars.
But that's where he talks about what he calls individual arts,
which are architecture,
sculpture, painting,
music, and poetry. Importantly, in that order,
because that's the order in which Hagel thinks he can
explain how humans increasingly come to take ownership of their own
um art. So I'm happy to talk about that later.
But anyway, so that's that in general
um is where
aesthetics and the philosophy of art fits in Hegel's system.
And the,
the other big claim that I make in my book on
Hagel's aesthetics is that we learn so much about Hagel's idealism
through his aesthetics.
So it's not just that OK, we get Hagel's system and then when we have time,
we can do the aesthetics. But if we don't understand the aesthetics,
we don't understand really crucial things about Hagel's theory of selfhood,
about feeling about perception, like
things that, that people usually talk about under the heading of, you know,
metaphysics or epistemology.
Um But I think there's a lot to learn about those more traditional fields. Um
Well, see, I shouldn't even say traditional fields because that,
that wasn't the case in Hegel's generation
that people thought that metaphysics and
epistemology were like the core philosophical
um enterprises and aesthetics was just derivative really
the opposite.
Um So it's more because of the way philosophy developed,
especially in the early 20th century
that we've come to think that um again, so part of what I'm,
what I try to do here is, is, is reorient us towards thinking about it the other way.
So there's something that you mentioned there that I would like to get more into.
So, and, and please correct me if I'm wrong. But it seems then that
in a way uh the way Hegel
approaches aesthetics,
I mean,
it's not as some sort of a separate field
or domain from all the other domains of philosophy,
like epistemology, probably ethics and metaphysics because
uh I mean, isn't it also
that
as Hegel uh understands art and aesthetics more generally,
that it ties very much to epistemology for example,
and how we understand the world and how we acquire knowledge about it.
Absolutely. Yeah, absolutely.
So we don't, there are things that we can only sort of know through our senses.
So that's an epistemological question. And there are ways in which
our status as embodied beings
can only be known to us through our senses. And so if we don't talk about
art,
we're not talking about a key part of epistemology.
And I think that Hagel has a pretty clear sense that our senses are, uh
again, it's not,
sometimes people think that Hagel thinks that we'd be best if
we were disembodied and I just think that's absolutely false.
Um So, in so far as part of what we know
is embodied and there is such a thing as embodied knowledge, this is where we get
it, we get it through aesthetics. And I should say,
you know, strangely, especially coming after
Kant and Shelling Hegel is completely uninterested in natural beauty.
Like he just doesn't even really want to talk about it.
Um
He,
he is almost exclusively interested in the philosophy of
art and in aesthetics as an artistic phenomenon.
Um But other people have certainly
talked a lot more about our aesthetic appreciation of nature.
And Schiller is a great example of that.
And it's always been very surprising to me that Hagel doesn't
engage with that conversation in Schiller more than he does.
Um But yes, absolutely. Um So like to give you an example when he talks about music,
music for
Hegel is the way we sense time.
And if you think about Kant,
talking about time is one of the two oper
intuitions through which that is necessary to our
understanding the world and having experience at all.
For Hegel. Music is the thing that in the, in the most pure sense allows us
to sense time
and since time is so critical to selfhood, so there's no selfhood without time
in a way. He thinks that music allows us to sense the self. I mean, it doesn't get more
root epistemological and metaphysical than that.
So what, what music allows us to do is have this very pure sense
of what is
so purely part of our existence, namely time.
And that Hagel thinks is why music literally
moves us,
I mean, literally and metaphorically. So you can be moved by music emotionally.
But Hagel himself says that
sometimes without knowing it, we'll start tapping our feet
when or moving our body.
I love that image of Hagel it like, you know,
we tended to give him as such a serious German philosopher and he was.
But um but he himself recognizing that sometimes he couldn't help but move,
you know, that that's really uh deep, deep knowledge of ourselves.
And again,
the knowledge without which I think Hagel thinks
our own understanding of ourselves would be impoverished.
That's all very interesting.
I mean,
oo one of the things that I find fascinating
about some philosophers is that nowadays through science,
we are confirming some of their ideas or intuitions, things that they've arrived at
uh without uh II, I mean, not through science as at least as we understand it today,
of course.
But for example, when you were talking there about
uh embodiment and embodied knowledge, I mean, nowadays,
we have an entire field of embodied
cognition and how we acquire knowledge
through, not just through operations that occur in our brain,
but through our brain being connected to the rest of our body and
how we move in the world and the actions we do and how we interact with things. And
I, I mean, it's really fascinating to me and uh
I mean, as I said, I'm more familiar with people like Nietzsche,
but even Nietzsche,
we could say was very much a philosopher of action.
I mean, he,
he loved to walk a lot and thinking while
he was walking and he talked about doing philosopher,
philosophy with a hammer and,
and they very much admire people of action.
And I, I mean, doing things instead of just
sitting and
thinking and have this sort of more
platonic vision of things that
perhaps we could or should in a way try to disembody ourselves,
which in a way seems very,
uh, uh, II, I mean, uh, the, there's a very interesting caricature of that.
I, I don't know if you ever watched the movie,
The Adventures Of Baron
Munchausen. But there's a,
there's a scene there played by Robin Williams where he's, uh,
uh, the king of the moon. I think it's the king of the moon, but the man on the moon
and he can separate his head from the rest
of the body just to try to become more enlightened
and it doesn't really work. So I think it's a very,
uh, a very funny parody of that sort of, uh disembodied
idea of
nationality or
epistemology. So,
yeah.
Yeah. And I do think that Hagel, despite his reputation, also resisted that kind of
reification of reason and of the mind.
Um, and, you know,
there's a lot of that in his philosophy of
subjective spirit too when he talks about anthropology and
um in psychology and ways in which
our minds are very formed by what happens around us.
And it talks about insanity in those passages as being very much tied to our embodied
um existence. So there's, there's way more of that in
HGL than most people think. And
again, I think the aesthetics are a wonderful way
to get at that. I mean, I'll, I'll say one other thing about it. I think
part of what Hagel really appreciated about art is that
we go through our everyday lives,
sensing things, but not being aware that we're sensing them.
So not being aware of ourselves as seeing and as hearing and as touching.
And when we do that,
I think Hagel thinks we risk beginning to treat the
world as something that's just out there that's a given.
You know, so
mcdowell and Brandon have been talking about this for a very long time.
Mcdowell, especially the myth of the given, right?
So the world is out there and what epistemology is, is just our,
like attaching our ideas to the outside world in uh in an accurate way.
And I think Hagel thinks that that that happens in part just out of habit, of course.
So when I walk by a tree, I can't every time think, wow, I'm seeing a tree.
And even though, you know, it seems this way from this perspective,
it's actually a different way from that.
Like I'd never get through my day.
Um But what art does is remind us of what our
senses are doing by disrupting that in really interesting ways.
So,
and one example would be looking at a painting
and realizing
that I can see three dimensions where there aren't three dimensions.
And that tells me something about the interaction of my mind with the world.
So we might think of a painting is
a paradigmatic example of something that just exists
independently outside of us.
But actually for it to exist
as a painting,
there has to be someone looking at it and perceiving it in a certain way.
And Hagel thinks that that kind of mutual formation between the self and the world
actually is what is true of us all day, every day.
But we get used to it,
it becomes and this is a really important technical term for him.
Prosaic,
right? We start to treat it as just sort of normal and given
and,
and, and as existing independently of us.
And what art reminds us is that in fact,
everything that we sense and everything that we do is
part of our mutual engagement and formation with the world.
And I think
Hegel famously doesn't articulate a theory of
aesthetic experience the way Khan does.
So, Kant says, you know,
it's the playing of the faculties and that's part of why it gives us pleasure is
because it gives us a break from our kind of prosaic parsing of the world Hagel
doesn't ever actually say that.
But I think what he
implies is that when we
are disrupted, out of our prosaic attitude towards the world
into a more aesthetic attitude towards it, we're actually sensing truth
in a way that we don't otherwise.
So if I go from just seeing the tree to having an aesthetic experience of the tree,
that's actually a more true experience of the tree. And that's part of what gives me
joy.
So
I think that's part of what Hagel thinks is going on
in all kinds of aesthetic pleasure.
So uh there was a point there uh in my previous question where you
mentioned the fact that at a certain point in his work on aesthetics,
Hegel talks about how humans can take
ownership of their art through specific kinds of
art. Could you tell us a little bit more about that?
Yeah. So this is behind his
trajectory from architecture to sculpture to what he calls
or actually it's one of his um editors.
But anyway, the three romantic arts which are painting music and poetry. So,
and many other philosophers like
Herder had put art into a different trajectory. So I think one really good way of
trying to figure out what Hagel is up to is to compare those and and you know,
why does he put what at the top?
Um So for Hegel architecture is the art form that feels most externalized to humans,
right?
So it's
big in scope.
It's also usually functional, although he often,
he also talks about architecture that's not functional.
Um
And it, it has to do primarily with matter
that seems independent of humans. So stone or brick or wood
and then sculpture also has a more um and an externalized material.
So whether that's marble or plaster or whatever,
but in sculpture, at least paradigmatic sculpture as Hagel understands it,
humans start to
reflect themselves in it.
So paradigmatic sculpture for Hegel is ancient Greek sculpture where um
humans are no longer making
uh like monstrous, exaggerated forms, but more just straight up human forms.
So that's, that's more attention to the human and more attention to the subjective.
And then when you get to painting music and poetry,
you're increasingly focusing humans attention on what's going
on inside of them as arts material.
So color
doesn't, I mean, it's let me put it this way.
It's more obvious to us that color doesn't exist in
the world the way that stone exists in the world.
OK.
So Hagel still doesn't think that we should
talk about stone as existing independently of us.
But leaving that aside,
painting more obviously points out to us our involvement in whatever is painted.
And so I already talked about like perspective, but that's true also of color.
And Hagel likes to talk about how
it's possible for a human to see a form like a human,
not even by drawing, but just by juxtaposing colors against each other.
So even if there isn't a human form drawn, if you juxtapose the colors,
a human will see
a drawing where there isn't one, right?
So again, more activity on the part of the subject
and then music, as I was saying a minute ago,
same thing. Music is totally interior, right?
So there we can't really talk about any material that's outside,
like we can talk about the instruments,
but the instruments aren't the music
and they certainly aren't my experience of the music. So that's
totally interior
and then poetry.
So Hagel and this is one of the the
interesting differences between Hagel and
other philosophers including Schopenhauer,
right?
So Schopenhauer puts music at the top because he wants really
to highlight
that kind of subjectivity. But Hagel is always interested in
the unity of identity
and difference, right? So he doesn't want to stop at subjectivity.
He wants to go back to
integrating subjectivity back into objectivity.
And so when we get to poetry, we have um
something that's 100% human creation, namely language
as material,
but it's,
it's not as subjective as music because language is something that you and I have to
agree on on some level.
Otherwise it wouldn't count as language if I just start, you know,
speaking gibberish,
that might be my private language,
but it's not going to function like language unless I'm in dialogue, literally,
not just with one person, but with a whole culture.
So then when we get to
as a kind of poetry,
which then embodies language as this very
human creation and this very mutually formed creation
back into action,
right? So then you have characters embodied characters back to embodiment,
embodied characters on a stage using language that's been mutually agreed upon,
not just between individuals but by a culture.
Then Hagel thinks we've got a
really profound experience of collective aesthetic creation
that can unite us as a community while also showcasing
the kind of subjectivity that a character like
Antigone or Hamlet is experiencing.
So, um
so that's the way in which Hagel,
that's why Hagel
orders them the way he orders them
and decides that drama is the most complete form of aesthetic experience,
which does not.
And we'll probably get to this in a minute. Um Mean that he thinks
that it's the best form of art,
but it is the highest aesthetic experience philosophically for humans.
You know, uh
while you were talking,
I was thinking at a certain point because you mentioned Schopenhauer there
that uh if um
uh I mean, of course, you probably already alluded to some of that in your answer. But
uh I was wondering what extent Hegel's statics
also connects to his metaphysics because when you mentioned
Schopenhauer,
I mean, Schopenhauer is um
a, at least for us more
modern contemporary people, it's a bit of a weird idea.
But uh if, if I understand it correctly. I think that,
uh OK, so, um Schopenhauer took that division from Kent,
uh the division between the Neuman
and, and the phenomenon
and the phenomenons uh the Ninon
sorry, supposedly is what reality itself is.
I mean, the fundamental nature of reality. And
uh and this is also something I, I guess that Nietzsche talks about in the,
the origin of tragedy because back then in his first book,
he was already very much influenced by Schopenhauer.
He then
uh uh
left some of that out of his philosophy later on. But
uh
didn't Schopenhauer have this sort of idea that
music itself was part of the fundamental nature
of reality.
Yeah. Absolutely. And that,
and for Schopenhauer,
the reason we love music so much and the reason it moves us
so much is because it is the most raw experience of reality we can
get.
And uh absolutely, it, it moves us because it is also, you know, and this is,
I think is, is the kind of thing Hagel thought too that
the joy that we get in it and in and its immediate access to our emotions so that
music can make us sad
about
nothing,
right?
So it's not if I listen to sad music, I'm not sad about anything. I'm just sad.
That's incredible. Like the fact that that's possible.
Schopenhauer thinks says something really profound about the nature
of reality and about the nature of being human.
And I think Hagel is attuned to that as well. And it doesn't
be again because he's more interested in
thinking about a society in which people work together. I mean,
Hagel,
I sometimes say to my students is just more
interested in like making sure that the society functions.
And so he's, he's much more interested in saying, OK,
what institutions are going to be necessary for us to create
a society in which humans can live to their full potential.
And someone like Schopenhauer, as I understand him is,
is just much less interested in that.
So I think Hagel wants to pull back from this kind of ra
education of subjectivity and say, OK,
it's really good.
It's really important
fundamental to modern humans.
Now, we've got to show how it can be fostered within institutions.
And so I think that's part of why um
music doesn't top the list for him
and to your original question about metaphysics. Absolutely.
I mean, this is the structure of reality as far as Hagel is concerned,
the identity of identity and difference.
And so the, the way in which the trajectory of the arts,
including music's subordinate place to drama
into poetry in general
is a
metaphysical commitment on Hagel's part. Absolutely.
Uh And uh I mean, you mentioned drama there.
Uh Did Hegel have specific views about tragedy and comedy?
Yes, this is something I thought about a lot. Um
And
probably many of your viewers will know that
Hagel is most famous for talking about tragedy.
So his
interpretation of antigone has been in particular,
very influential. And I mean,
the thousands of pages that have been written on that are testament to how,
how important and revelatory his theory of tragedy was.
But
um much less attention has been paid to his theory of comedy.
And so I got really interested in that at a certain point.
Um Both what Hagel says about comedy and why it has been um not taken as seriously,
really quick answer to the second question that's just really typical that
philosophers um tend to take serious things more seriously. And
unless you want to take comedy seriously
and therefore risk being comic yourself because
how ridiculous is it to take comedy seriously?
Um People don't do it. I, I have uh spent probably more time in my life than I should
taking comedy very seriously. I teach a course on it. Um
And that, that is in part because I,
yeah, I got interested in what Hagel says about tragedy and comedy.
So in short,
and I'm much more focused on what he says about it in
his lectures on aesthetics rather than what he says in the phenomenology.
But I do think they are,
they are connected
tragedy for Hegel
shows a kind of subjectivity,
very
entrenched in itself and in roles in particular in like social roles.
So if you think about antigone,
she is struggling with her role as a daughter
and as a sister
and as a subject, right?
So her brothers have been killed, she wants to bury one of them.
She feels that that's her duty.
Her uncle, the king
is also her king now and she's supposed to obey him and he forbids this, um,
since one of her brothers was a traitor.
So the, the tragedy there is between
two people who are deeply invested in their subjective
relationships to their roles and those roles are incompatible.
So there's no way for it to end without one of them
dying.
Um It's not several people die, but you know, of the two of them, only one of them dies.
And so I, but
in so far as Hegel
is always interested in the unity of unity and division.
What you get there is two people whose conflict with each other cancels
itself out and then what you get at the end the synthesis.
Although Hagel doesn't use that word
is the survival of the Greek City state
with increased knowledge of how those roles have to be treated within the Polish.
So Creon ends the play essentially admitting that he
shouldn't have had the attitude that he had to
his role.
So,
so for Hagel, the reason that tragedy is art is because it shows this clash,
which ends in a kind of unification
comedy,
also ancient comedy and Hagel's favorite is Aristophanes
also ends in reunification.
But it's because like if you take streps
sides as an example in the clouds, he doesn't take himself so seriously.
So he, you know, kind of goofs around and he undermines the city and then, you know,
he cheats and he,
and he's never like fixed on his role and that gives him an enormous amount of power.
And so in the clouds, in particular, you also see the, like
the beginning of the erosion of the idea that the
gods are really in control because they're being mocked in strips
and, and they had been before, this isn't new in Aristophanes necessarily.
But at the end of that, you get a kind of cheerful reunification.
And Hegel actually says, um
at another point,
you know, maybe that's better,
you know, why would we choose the dark
and um desperate conflict of tragedy over the cheerful life affirming?
And I think there's a lot of this in Nietzsche
too,
life affirming laughter of someone who doesn't have to be so beholden to
his roles that he's willing to bring the whole society down around him.
So there's a, there's a, an extended story that I'm happy to tell if,
if you're interested um about how
that
changes in modern tragedy and modern comedy.
Um But Hagel is pretty pessimistic about both
mo modern tragedy and modern comedy.
Um And essentially, I think,
thinks that we're going to have to transcend both of them or,
and this is another big topic, move to more of a humor based aesthetic than a
comedy based aesthetic,
right?
Uh I'm going to ask you more about that, about modern comedy and tragedy in a second.
But I, I mean, I just wanted to make a brief comment because this was
to some extent, I mean, uh the, the way people like Hegel,
Schopenhauer Nietzsche
and others in the 19th century approached
uh aesthetics and art uh somewhat reminds me of
uh how dismissive uh the
post
Socratic were of the Pres
Socratic
because the Pre
Socratic took the poets and uh seriously when it comes to
uh
I mean, perhaps uh also being able to acquire some sort of
knowledge through art, through fiction and all of that. And
I, and I, and I mean, of course, I,
I don't think we can really be sure about what part
of it came from Socrates or Plato because sometimes we don't know
for sure if it's Socrates or Plato talking, but in Plato's works.
But anyway, I, I mean,
the Socrates
and the,
the other Greek philosophers who came after
him were very dismissive of Homer specifically and
the other poets. And when you think about the Pres
Socratic and even
what we
call the Sophists, I, I mean, nowadays,
sophistry has a very negative connotation to it, but the Sophists
were very much philosophers themselves, I think.
Uh so I, I wa I was just, I mean, it just came to my mind that uh there are,
there have been periods in
Western philosophy, where people have very much been dismissive of art,
at least as a potential source of some kind of knowledge and
others where people really engaged
with art seriously and philosophically took art seriously.
Yeah. Absolutely.
Yeah. And I think this is the 19th century, is one
place where that pen direction.
So tell us about the issues that Hegel had with modern
forms of art, particularly
uh with what we could call,
I guess modern subjectivity in art because uh
as time went on and particularly since the,
I guess, more or less the 19th century onwards,
I mean, in literature and other forms of art,
we see people focusing more on
particular characters and character development and
there's objectivity even what goes on
in their minds through ex through lots and lots of,
of, of texts sometimes just focusing on their inner thoughts and all of that.
II, I guess that's what we could call a
modern subjectivity in art to uh or perhaps
there's also some other forms of subjectivity.
But what did Hegel
think about it?
I think one of the best places to isolate that is in what he says about humor. And
yeah, and I think
humor was a really new
aesthetic phenomenon.
It essentially began with Lawrence Stern's Tristam Shandy,
which was enormously popular in Germany. I mean,
Goethe
and
Schiller and Lessing and anybody who was anybody
um loved Stern and his evocation of characters
who were not comic in the classic sense of like, Aristophanes.
Um,
but were kind of quirky and had foibles and eccentricities
that made you kind of gently laugh at them.
So, not mock them, not
guffaw
but,
but just recognize how much humans get obsessed
with what stern called their hobby horses.
Like their little
things that they're, the, the little things that they wanna be obsessed about.
So, you know, whether it's your train set or his, you know, his uncle's military,
uh what
was it? It wasn't exactly a
like models, I guess. Anyway, um
So Hagel thought
that comedy and, and humor needed to be differentiated as,
as did um pretty much everybody in his
um generation.
So comedy as a kind of dramatic art form
and humor as something that more suffused literature and poetry
and that highlighted
again this sense that
what is really important to pay attention to among humans now
is that since we've discovered as it were that
we are the source of meaning in the world,
what is meaningful to us and how
kind of adorably silly that often is like how adorably silly
many of our concerns are.
And I think Hegel thought that was really valuable aesthetically
because it brought attention to, you know, the the concerns of art are no longer
the gods or big battles or even like sublime landscapes,
but like Dutch genre paintings or still lifes that
show tiny little involved human obsessions with flowers or
having your tooth pulled or, you know, like everyday human things,
but he did not like it when people became so subjective
that they didn't try to
extract any larger meaning from whatever it was that they were doing.
So he was very critical of Jean Paul Richter on this point,
very critical of people like Schlegel,
Friedrich
Schlegel. And you know, to a lesser extent, people like Novalis
who Hagel thought were way too focused on their own interiority
and stream of consciousness essentially as you were just describing
and therefore, again,
never made the connection back from
subjectivity back into objectivity and therefore,
were not giving their
audiences an experience of the truth. So that's always what's at stake for Hagel.
Um So he's very critical of what he calls subjective humor
and very admiring of what he calls objective humor.
Do you think that Hagel would have been a, a fan?
Or at least like to some extent the existentialists,
do you think that Hegel would have been a,
a fan or at least like to some extent the existentialists?
I'm not so sure he would have been to be honest with you. I think he,
he, as I said earlier,
he was really interested in making a society function on an institutional level.
So what kind of form of government do we need?
What kind of um social order, what kind of economic order,
what kind of family situation
and in so far as existentialists and this is generalizing but
often
emphasize the subject in opposition to those things.
I think Hagel would have
again, felt like, well, but what we're after here is truth,
which is the unity of unity and division, not just division.
And we have a world to run like it's our responsibility to run this world.
There's no God out there to help us out,
there's no natural order like we've got to get this right.
And if there's, and again, this is to caricature. But
if existentialists are sometimes seen as self obsessed or just as oppositional to
the order,
I think Hagel would have been much more interested in reforming the order in
ways that would better allow humans to be free and the way he thought
humans needed to be free. And that back to something we were saying a minute ago,
I think this is something that Marx picks up from. Hagel is very much about
what kind of material conditions do humans need in order to be free.
So it's not enough
to say as Kant did um that you're free if you're self determining
and can act against your inclinations
in accordance with the categorical imperative.
I realize that Kant scholars are going to say that that's not all he meant.
And, and I accept that, but Hagel was much more explicit
in trying to say what real freedom means is paying
attention to what people need in institutions around them.
And
you know, just life forms around them in order to be, to flourish as
humans with dignity and respect.
So again, that's maybe too hard on the existentialist.
But I, I think that might be his general take.
That's very interesting because o of course,
we know that Marx was influenced by Hegel
to some extent,
but sometimes because people have these simplistic views of
Hegel and Marx they think, oh, how could it be?
Because Hegel was supposedly a big idealist and Marx was a me
realist. I mean, how could they be more opposite?
But uh I mean,
what you mentioned there and uh Hegel caring
very much about how we structure society,
about
the institutions we create and how we create them based on
what
values, I guess.
Uh I mean, it's very much uh
I guess also applied philosophy or political philosophy
as some of what Marx also cared about.
Absolutely. And I,
you know,
I think another thing that you can find in Hegel that I think is just much more
clearly articulated in Marx is that freedom can be a kind of
ideological lie
if
you continue to tell people that they're free as a
way of distracting them from the fact that they're being exploited
and alienated, right? So if you make people focus on,
yes,
but I'm a free and determining being
because I can follow the categorical imperative,
which I, I again, that's a caricature.
Um Then people are going to feel like, well, you know,
who cares what sort of deprived economic situation I live in.
I'm still free and Hagel, I think, worried
that
that kind, that,
that kind of idea could fall into the wrong
hands of people who knew how to manipulate it.
Such that
exactly as you said, you know, you can be a, a worker who's being totally exploited.
But as long as you're told that there's a kind of freedom that exists
in transcending that or not caring about it or, or that actually,
you know what it is to be human is to,
to subsist despite the struggle of economic depravity,
I think Hagel also would say that's just,
that's manipulative, it's deceitful and it's unethical.
Uh it's, it's, it is not, it is false freedom, it is empty, fake, false freedom.
And it can be a kind of uh a tool in the hands of people
who want to manipulate others into ignoring
the ways in which they're being exploited,
which is very interesting because I guess that this is also another
idea that people do not tend at all to associate with Hegel.
But as Marx, he also cared about
the poverty, right?
And about the causes of poverty and the
potential effects it would have on people's behavior.
Correct.
Yeah.
So this is specifically in the passages where
he talks about what's called the rabble.
And, and I think this is again, a distinction that Marx picks up on
that what Hagel means by the rabble is not just people who are impoverished. So
and Hagel, like many people thinks that there will always be
poverty.
But what's new
since, you know,
well, not new now, but new since the modern world essentially
is the claim that all humans are worthy of dignity and respect
and the acknowledgement or just the fact that our economies are human
creations.
So whereas poverty before could be explained just by natural phenomenon
or just by a hierarchy that we were told was natural.
You know, the king gets to be rich and you have to be poor
because God made him the king and made you a pauper.
Now, the combination of the claim that all humans are worthy of dignity and respect
and a human created economy,
that means that many people live in total depravity
generates a kind of
rage on the part of
what Hagel then calls the rabble. Um that is entirely justified
and that Hagel sees as a pretty existential
threat to modern society because they're right,
right. It's, it's not that we need them
to get over this fact that they're right about it.
And as long as that's true, they,
you know, society will be unstable because they will correctly demand
the material conditions.
For the thing that they're told is their kind of existential, right.
So in HGL talks about ways to solve that through essentially what
we would call labor unions or other forms within civil society that would
and within the government
that would represent not just geographical
interests but economic interests.
So when, when you look at what Hagel says about the form the state should take,
I think one of the most overlooked facts
is that he does not want purely geographical representation.
He doesn't want, you know,
Prussia gets two delegates and Bavaria gets two delegates and no
following is two delegates but
that different classes and different
kinds of um
of industry get representation.
So that to me is very clear evidence that he
was worried about not just the material conditions of capitalism,
but also the questions of identity and self-respect
that are necessary in the modern work world
um that are essentially trampled on by capitalism.
And so um could we say that Hegel like Marx was also
or thought that it was a moral imperative for society to try
as best as we could to alleviate or ideally eradicate poverty?
Yeah, absolutely. I I don't think Hale
thought it could be completely eradicated. But
um yeah,
I there's no question in my mind that he saw
this as the deepest and most insidious kind of hypocrisy
that a society would say on the one hand that everyone is equal and
deserving of dignity and respect and then continue
to choose
um an an economic system
that made that a joke, right? And it's very bad joke, a sad joke.
Um It made it laughable in the worst possible way.
And that a society that
continues down that road is both
morally
responsible and in danger of instability.
So I do, I do think Hagel thinks those two things are separate.
So a better functioning society is going to be 11 with less inequality.
But also that totally aside, just as a moral issue. Um yeah, this is a classic failure
and just to be totally clear because at a certain point there,
you mentioned the fact that some of these ideas stem from
the more general idea that
people, individual, people themselves have intrinsic value.
I mean, this is not just a matter of
caring about alleviating poverty with the
long term success of a particular society in mind, but also caring
actually about the individuals themselves and the conditions
they live in.
Yes and their emotional and
effective attachment to their value as workers.
So when he starts to talk about solutions to this kind of poverty, he says,
you know,
you can certainly get government agencies involved in essentially welfare,
but that's not going to fix the problem of self-respect.
You have to give people
the possibility of having dignity in their work if work is going
to be such a central part of existence in a capitalist system.
Um And so yeah, ju I mean,
just trying to eradicate it through philanthropy is
also not going to fix the problem.
It has to come at the level of actually valuing workers in their roles as workers.
Oh my God. So it was not just that Marx was an
alien but Hagel was also a Marxist.
Well, not everybody would agree with me.
But, but, yeah, I mean, I, I think that's all, that's all very clear to me.
Um, that, that is part of what Hagel was concerned about and, you know,
there are places in his philosophy where he is also guilty of that kind of hypocrisy.
So it's not as if he had some sort of moral
genius that allowed him to see that in other parts of his
life.
But I,
I think that was one place where he really did see
the dangers that we are living with very presently now.
Yeah. No, but I mean, I, I made, I made that sort of a joke but,
uh, uh, I, if, uh, he's, if you didn't mention his name,
just everything you said about poverty and capitalism that
we should structure society and all of that,
I mean,
if someone told me it was Marx to,
I
won't believe it.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
I think that's true and that would be true until we started talking about the state.
Right.
So Hagel talks about all of this when he's talking about civil society,
which is the middle one of the.
So he talks about the family and civil society and the state
and its,
when he starts to talk about the state that you
would no longer think we were talking about Marx.
Great.
So, uh we've already talked here a little bit about uh comedy,
but one of the things you've also done work on, uh and again, focusing on
uh 19th century German philosophy is how
seriously some of these philosophers took laughter.
Right.
Yeah.
Or we might say like the laughable because it,
it's so hard to put all of the things that we laugh at under uh and,
and a lot of things that are laughable, we don't actually laugh at.
So it's, it's a very thorny um
topic. But, but yes, especially around the time when Hagel was writing.
Um again, people like
Schlegel,
um and some of the other more romantic philosophers like Zolar
um were taking this question of what we laugh at and why or,
or what it means to differentiate between wit
and irony and humor really seriously.
And I think that, uh you know, Lessing was another one who took this very seriously.
Um
Eta Hoffman, like the whole constellation of people who were philosophical,
but also writing in literature.
Um
And I think again, it comes back to this question, like,
what does it say about humans that we laugh?
And what does it say about us that we find
this whole range of things either funny or laughable?
And what could we determine about the essence of what it is to be human
by really trying to figure that out?
And if you're someone like
Schlegel
who thinks that Hegel is wrong
to imagine that we can articulate truth in philosophy,
then you're going to be looking towards other forms that maybe as
Schlegel would sort of put it gesture at the truth
while not articulating it.
Because articulating it is always going to
introduce new categories and therefore new division.
So if the true is the whole, I think Schlegel
would say to Hegel,
um
any conceptualization is just going to show the division again.
And if you want something that retains the unity,
it has to remain at the level of affect or
something like
irony,
which doesn't take itself too seriously and doesn't define things,
but sort of says that things are true through saying they're opposite
or says something that's witty in a way that
you don't take literally, but you see the truth behind it.
Um So all of these are ways in which a whole range of people
in the romantic generation
decided that if we could understand that and the way that functions in the way humans
interact with each other and lead our aesthetic lives,
then we could probably understand something
much deeper about humans themselves and about
metaphysics quite honestly.
Um So there's a lot of um I edited a volume of essays about
uh humor in the 19th century. And as I say in the introduction,
usually when I tell people that they laugh because
um one of the things we laugh at is incongruity
and it feels so incongruous to talk about
humor in this generation of very serious philosophers,
but it is something they took really seriously.
And I mean,
trying to understand something about our human nature through laughter.
I mean, there are many different ways we can try to understand it. Right.
And I mean, even philosophers themselves,
many different philosophers across history
uh
have had different theories about why people laugh
at something. And,
uh, I, I mean, perhaps all of them are true.
I don't know because some,
we laugh at different things in different contexts for different reasons.
I mean,
sometimes we might laugh at something because it's
funny and why it's funny is an entire
question by itself. But
uh sometimes perhaps people laugh at someone to mock them.
Not exactly because it's funny, but just to mock them or
to feel superior to other people, perhaps something,
someone does something wrong.
Uh And they are, I mean,
competing with them and then the other person laughs just because, oh,
you made the mistake.
So I'm in a, in a better situation than you are or something like that. So,
I mean, the, uh just thinking about laughter itself and
the many different contexts and reasons why people laugh is, uh,
I mean, it's, it's a very
wide
uh field of inquiry, I guess.
Yeah, absolutely.
Yeah.
OK. So, um let's get now into uh
how you got interested
in abolitionism
in America in the 19th century. So, tell us first about that.
What got you interested in that and then
we'll get into the work of Lydia Maria Child.
Yeah,
this was, um, a very direct
response on my part to the 2016 election in the United States.
So when, when Donald Trump was elected,
um it became very clear to many of us that
we were in a kind of moral and political emergency.
Uh So the real resurgence of a kind of far right,
political stance and all of the other things that Trump represented,
including his um just open derision of and abuse of women.
And
I think as a Hagel scholar,
I've always had to grapple a little bit with
what, how I felt when I would read Hagel scholarship from
the 19 thirties.
And I would always
have in the back of my mind,
what did this person think they were doing?
Um was what they were doing more important than anything they could have been doing
to fight the rise of fascism in Germany.
Um And I don't pretend I don't mean to be judgmental.
I'm sure people have all kinds of reasons, et cetera, but
I just had a very clear sense very quickly that I
needed my professional life and my scholarship to
reflect the time that I was living in.
And I had a,
I wanted to know who in my own country and in my own history.
Um I could turn to as an example of someone who had faced a moral emergency in
their country.
Head on. And I just decided I wanted to turn to women. I'd spent 20 years of my career
really exclusively focusing on men. And so I, I asked myself
to fight something as entrenched as enslavement was in the United States
in the 19th century.
I just thought you'd have to be thinking philosophically,
you'd have to be asking big questions like,
what is equality, what is justice? What does it mean to be a human?
What is moral obligation? Um
So I went to an archive associated with Harvard and
that, that is a, a library and an archive specifically about women and
asked if they knew of any
women with a kind of philosophical
uh trajectory who had been involved in abolitionism and they didn't.
But they gave me a box of letters that included
a letter by this woman who I'd never heard of,
but um was immediately just transfixed by her moral vision,
her ability to argue philosophically
um and her ability to dedicate her life to
ending
entrenched evil in her country. So
I decided to pivot towards doing something about her.
And at first I, I did write a couple of more academic articles about her.
She was definitely a philosophical thinker. She also talked about philosophy.
She read philosophy, she was very influenced by German philosophy.
Um She regularly cites Schiller and Goethe
and Harrier
and John Paul. She mentions Kant,
she mentions Hegel.
German philosophy was very popular in the United States. Um,
in the 18 thirties and forties when she started writing.
So I had a lot of pretty instant connections to her philosophical thinking.
But what really again
got my attention was she wrote a book in 18 33
and that's almost three decades before the American Civil War started.
So in 18 33 he wrote a book called
An Appeal in Favor of that class of Americans called Africans.
And this, this is just a fire hose of arguments denouncing
all of the bad arguments that Americans had been using
to justify slavery.
And I was so impressed by how she,
I think her general philosophical commitment was
to thinking that humans are basically good,
but they're susceptible to bad arguments that appeal to their selfishness,
their self interest, their vanity.
And if you can just clear away those arguments,
you can really
get them to reform. I'm not sure she was right about that.
I don't even think she thought she was right about that by the end of her life.
Um But I became really fascinated both by her as a philosophical thinker,
but also as a woman whose life intersects in
all of the major moments leading up to and through the American
Civil War.
Um
She did everything from put her body between abolitionist speakers and anti
abolitionist mobs.
She wrote fiction and also argumentative essays.
She wrote biographies, she wrote histories.
Um She volunteered herself raising money for and sewing for
both union soldiers and,
um, enslaved peoples. So she, um,
she was,
she is,
to me a real example of someone who took her role as an American citizen seriously
and deployed everything she could think of,
uh, to address what she saw as the great moral crisis in her country.
So I wrote a biography of her. Um,
again, I, I thought I would just sort of write academic articles about her, but
the story is so compelling that I ended up writing the
whole thing and that came out um about six months ago.
Great. Uh And II, I mean, uh
we also have to keep in mind that the 19th century
was not
to, to put it mildly
very women friendly and also for the most part, not very friendly to
any person who was not of European descent,
basically in, in terms of the mainstream philosophers, thinkers,
scientists and so on.
Uh I mean, of course, we have to keep also in mind the cultural context back then.
And I,
I'm also not one of those people who,
of course, I say that that they were wrong in terms of their sexism and racism.
But I don't think that
if I lived back then I wouldn't
have been racist and sexist myself, of course,
very likely I would have been one as well and
most of us, I guess so.
Uh But I mean, we have to keep that, keep that in mind but also
the struggle that women and, uh,
but,
uh African Americans and other minorities went through and particularly since
we are approaching things here from a philosophical perspective
and I am talking with U as an academic,
I mean,
it's historically, it's a fact and even con temporarily that,
uh,
women and, uh, other minorities,
uh, I mean, their work has very much been neglected, sometimes suppressed and,
uh, stuff like that. Right. So, it's, it's not been easy at all for
people who are not
European white
males and European white males,
particularly from the upper classes to have their voices heard.
Yeah.
Yeah. And, and there's really wonderful work being done on that. So, um Kristen Yah
and Dal
and Nassar just last year published a whole anthology of
work by women philosophers in Germany in the 19th century.
And Alison Stone and I are working on a handbook
about British and American women philosophers in the 19th century.
There were many more of them than we think there were.
And they were often much better known than we think they were.
So, what we're talking about is a combination of, of course,
women didn't have the same opportunities as men as far as education
goes.
But they,
but even those who manage to philosophize despite that were pretty actively
repressed and forgotten later, like not in their lifetimes but later. So,
so there's a lot of really interesting work on that. Um
that I I feel very passionate about.
And I, I also think to your other point,
it's really important for us to acknowledge in as much
detail as we can
the damage that people like Hagel did on these topics.
So I think even myself as a woman,
I used to just sort of think, well, of course,
he thought women were like plants like everybody did,
but that's not true.
There were lots of people including women who didn't think that, but there were,
he did have options available to him and even more so on race.
So there's a, there's really important work by Daniel James and Franz
Kopek
and um
and,
and others on what Hagel probably did know about other ways of thinking about non
European peoples which he deliberately chose to ignore or suppress.
And there's even terrible stories about Hagel.
Hagel's like philosophy of history being used as a justification
in the United States for perpetuating slavery.
And, you know, I was talking earlier about Hagel's ability to pinpoint hypocrisies
um between in a culture that said on the one hand,
all humans are worthy of dignity and respect.
And on the other hand, subjecting them to
capitalism's woes. Obviously, Hagel himself is horrendously guilty of doing that
pretty much with anyone who wasn't, as you said, an upper class white European male.
Um And I have become much less willing just to say, wow, OK,
that's like a part of his philosophy, we can ignore
um and much more determined to take that head on
and, and as you say, too importantly, augmented with a kind of humility
that
reminds myself as well,
that I'm probably on the wrong side of history on other things.
And that, um
if I were living at Hegel's time,
I probably would have had many opinions that were not very enlightened
either.
So, to me, that's part of the,
the general project of thinking about the 19th
century is elevating voices like childs that are
um
so philosophical and so resonant and using the same kinds of ideas,
including ideas about art
that Hagel was interested in,
but really in the service of good
and trying to be much more mindful and critical of ways in which
Hegel's philosophy is beautiful and compelling as it can be um was used for evil.
Yeah.
Uh
I mean,
this is another entire discussion that I think
is very interesting that people can have.
I mean, uh and the same applies to artists.
I mean,
sometimes people discuss if what we should do with the work of immoral artists,
if we should ban it, if not, if we, if we don't ban it,
uh we should analyze it.
Uh We should think of it if we should appreciate
it or not and if we should criticize it,
uh I mean, there's uh an immensity of questions out there
that are very interesting about that.
But, but uh uh I mean, of course, Uh
I'm not myself and I don't think you are some of those people.
I think that perhaps we should be because
someone in the 19th century or the 18th century
had some appalling views on women and uh black
people and other minorities that we should just,
uh,
I
completely ignore or think that the rest of their work is,
doesn't have any
intellectual valid
validity at all. But,
uh yeah, it's very much a well
established fact that
all of the
people we talked about in German philosophy in the 19th century and
Kent was mostly from the 18th century and,
and others like them. Uh I, I mean, I, I
it,
it's interesting that even Kent was talking about
universal values but apparently they didn't apply to
uh non
European people
uh curiously enough. But,
but I, I mean, the same thing I guess happened in other sorts of instances, like,
for example,
you have the French revolution and supposedly everyone should get a vote,
everyone should get the same.
But it was just
very gradually that the population in France, uh
the adult population
got to AAA right to vote. I mean, first it was just
uh one slice of the male population and then, and the same in happened in America,
I think, I think that initially it was just the,
the people who, who owned land, I guess
-- whether the right to vote and then it was, yeah, all
-- of that was in flux.
For a very long time here. That's true.
And, and the other thing to bring up,
I think in the context of the French revolution is the Haitian revolution.
And the fact that France absolutely did
not want any of their revolutionary principles to
apply to a part of the world that was primarily inhabited by Black people.
Um So that,
that's another classic case of um of the kind of hypocrisy that I think you're right.
To me,
it just feels increasingly important to
acknowledge those problems always and upfront.
And in every part of our discussion of these earlier thinkers,
um and never to treat it as something we can just
sort of mention on the side and then move on from.
Um But I don't think that ignoring these people is good either because
it's important for us to remember that even people who were intelligent and
progressive in other ways um could make really horrendous mistakes.
And I,
and I guess that I it's not only important from
a sort of ethical standpoint but also intellectually speaking,
I guess it's enriching uh to
uh have a better understanding of how our
socio cultural context can influence and have an impact
on our
-- intellectual work, I guess.
-- Absolutely.
Yeah, we, we need to understand why we think what we think
and understanding thinkers that came before us is
an indispensable part of that for sure.
A a and also
keeping in keeping in mind that again,
people are not disembodied beings and we live and we not only have a body
but we also live in a particular society in a particular period of time,
in a particular culture,
we have a ton of different in influences and we are also products of all of that
even intellectually. It's not that we have some sort of
reasoning faculty
that, that is impermeable to all of that and that allow us to get
some sort of glimpse into objective reality as it is.
Yeah.
And I, I'll also just say briefly,
that's one of the things that really fascinates me about child is that
she was able in many ways to transcend and to
see beyond what was absolutely the norm around her.
And I'm really fascinated by that.
Um And I,
you know, most of your viewers will know that.
Um So she grew up in Boston, which is in the north
and most northerners now
assume
that all northerners then were against slavery. And that's absolutely not true.
Absolutely not true.
Many northerners actively resisted the end of slavery in the South.
So she was surrounded by politicians and
educators and journalists and religious leaders who
actively preached that this was an acceptable way for society to be organized.
And somehow she saw beyond it. And she, you know, she wasn't alone in that.
And I'll also say
part of how she knew this is she actually talked to black people,
right? So she actually listened to the people who were themselves affected.
And once was able to see it from their point of view,
realized that what she was hearing from the
leaders in her society was, was wrong.
So again, I don't mean to suggest that she had some sort of, as you say,
disembodied um experience,
but she was willing to listen in a way that I take as an inspiration
to those of us who sometimes
it's a kind of occupational hazard for philosophers.
We like to look at things from very high up.
And often I think it takes more of a listening on the ground
to um get real ethical insight into what needs to happen next.
By the way, at least back in her time, how influential
was her, I mean, in the philosophical world and more specifically
in the abolitionist movement in the US,
she was very influential.
She, she was one of the most famous abolitionists um of the 19th century.
And, and part of what's so interesting about her is that she was famous before.
She became an abolitionist because she
um
almost unheard of in the American 19th century by the age of 22
which would have been, you know, in the
mid 18 twenties, was a very well known novelist and a self sufficient female author.
And she'd written a couple novels and a couple of self-help books,
um like cooking books or books about parenting or housekeeping
um that had made her really beloved and trusted along among a great swath.
I mean, she was the 19th century equivalent of a household name.
Um And when she became an abolitionist,
that was so upsetting to her readers because it really meant that she was a radical
because to be,
to be an abolitionist in the 18 twenties and thirties in the United States
was to argue for the immediate end of slavery without compensation to enslavers
and most Americans in the North and the
South thought that that was just unthinkably radical.
Um
But she, that's what she was convinced. And, you know, by the time she was about 30
she continued to be one of the best published and
most um public facing intellectuals of the 19th century.
And certainly in the abolitionist movement
as far as her involvement in the philosophical community, it's interesting,
I mean, there wasn't so much like philosophical
tradition in the United States except really for the one that
was getting going again in Boston around Ralph Waldo Emerson.
And they did know each other.
They were almost exact contemporaries and she was
admiring and would go to his lectures.
Um But also was always concerned that he
was allowing the abstraction of his thought to distract
him from what she thought he should be doing,
which was fighting slavery.
So she'd sometimes say he has a platform big enough and a mind capacious enough
really to make arguments against slavery and he's not
doing it.
Um Emerson did come around to doing that but only in 18 59
when John Brown's failed insurrection in Virginia
uh convinced him that slavery needed to be um opposed.
So she,
she certainly knew all of the philosophers in the
Boston area of her time and socialized with them,
communicated with them,
but I think she feared that they had disengaged themselves from
the moral topics of their day. Too much.
OK. So uh I, I'm also getting mindful of your time now.
So let me ask you, let me ask you one last question. Uh And let me see if, if I can
phrase this correctly. So,
uh and be clear about it. Uh
So, uh I mean, there are
some parts of philosophy
that are politically motivated, like for example,
abolitionism is a very clear example of that.
And
there are people that tend to be a little bit
dismissive of philosophy that is done while politically motivated.
And usually those people from come from
political positions that are opposite
to the, to the ones that they say are not valid philosophy, of course. So
the question I wanted to ask you then is
how do you look at the place of a movement like abolitionism
uh
in the broader
historical context of philosophy? And
uh uh
I mean, when it comes to how people look again at politically motivated philosophy,
I mean,
to what extent
do you think
we should take it
seriously? And, I mean, what do you think basically about
those people's position, the positions that,
oh, I, I mean, philosophy should be
about,
I don't know people in academia.
I, I mean, it's, uh, transmitting knowledge to students shouldn't be about, uh,
turning them into activists or something like that.
So,
uh, I, I mean, I, I hope I'm being clear in terms of the question I'm asking here.
But what are your thoughts on it?
Yeah, thank you.
It's such a, it's such an important question to me uh now,
so I appreciate the chance to
think about it. Um
I guess
a couple of things, first of all,
philosophy has not always been removed from reality.
And I think like the story of the 19th century into the 20th century
uh is
much more about philosophy deciding to extract itself from practice.
And there are historical reasons for that,
but I think we're wrong if we assume and I this isn't what you were saying either.
But I think some of the people you're thinking about would say this, that,
that real philosophy
shouldn't dirty its hands or shouldn't kind of get involved
in the world because then it's not as pure,
that's, that's a choice that philosophy has made
relatively recently as a discipline and it
has to do with the professionalization of philosophy
um in the 19th century, in the United States.
Well, the three cases I know most about are the US, the UK and Germany,
you, you couldn't get a degree in philosophy no matter who you were in for a long time.
Right. Phd.
S weren't invented that long ago and even after they were invented, they weren't
necessary to philosophizing philosophical journals did not
use to require that you came from.
Um,
you had a phd in philosophy to
publish.
So, so the,
the professionalization of philosophy has meant that what it means
to do philosophy has gotten narrower and narrower and narrower,
more elitist, more professionalized.
But there's a very long history of philosophy being born out of
grappling with the real world as it were.
Um And I don't think there's been a social movement
in history that hasn't required people to think philosophically.
Um I mean, Angela Davis is a great example of someone who
uh was doing a phd in philosophy before she became
an activist and brought her um studies in Spinoza and
Kant and Hegel to her struggle for racial justice in the United States.
But I think pretty much anywhere you look, you would find
people who are fighting for justice thinking philosophically.
And I've been very happy to see people emphasizing that more.
So people are writing about Martin Luther King as a philosopher for instance.
-- Um
-- And yeah,
I was going to say that perhaps another excellent example would
be the civil rights movement in the 19 sixties and seventies.
-- Yeah,
-- exactly. So,
so I think a,
a
more or an alternate model and I think in some ways,
a truer model to philosophy's history is that
when people are confronted with injustices,
they have to ask those bigger questions.
And I think what philosophy can do to empower us
is to give us some clarity about those questions.
So, you know, really what is justice?
Um you know, we can go back to the Republic to find people trying to figure that out.
And so when I teach philosophy,
I don't at all think of myself as trying to turn my students into activists.
But I do think that I want them to see
that philosophy can be a really powerful and even essential tool
for understanding the terms of our debates and
the kinds of things we want to fight for
and then giving us the clarity of thought
that can motivate
action.
So when, when I think about the way movements
work,
sometimes what happens is people just aren't
particularly clear what they're fighting for and why
and what that means is that whenever there's infighting or tension or unclear,
like you can just lose focus and get,
you know, distracted by the details. But the better you are
at saying no, I thought this through philosophically,
even if you don't phrase it that way.
This is what is important, this is what back to Hagel
really creating a society in which people can
truly be free and not just abstractly free.
This is what it would look like
that that is empowering and motivating
in a way that can help us stave off the kind of burnout or fatalism
that is all too often the death of movements for justice.
So I would prefer to think philosophy is as something that is born out of
humans, just trying to figure our way out in the world.
And the more those of us who are inclined to think philosophically can
articulate those thoughts and help people think them through.
I think the better chance philosophy has of
actually fulfilling a good purpose in the world.
Yeah, a and perhaps, I mean, people who might be worried uh
about
keeping some of the
philosophical traditions of the West, perhaps they should also keep in mind that
if Plato is the father of Western philosophy, then
he wrote a book titled The Republic,
which
which I I it would be very hard to argue that it's
not politically motivated because it's literally a book about how to,
to, to structure politically a society from top to bottom.
So,
-- yeah,
-- very
good.
Yeah, absolutely. And the more I think we recognize that
philosophy has been done in many different ways.
So like the academic article
really new,
I mean,
we think about like Plato writing and dialogues
and Aristotle giving lectures and you know,
k
writing something more that we recognize as philosophy,
but people writing philosophically through literature, Nietzsche
through aphorisms, like
many of our most important philosophers have been
really disruptive of what people thought philosophy was.
And so I, I do not feel like my time is well spent fighting for
a version of philosophy that I think is pretty historically contingent,
sometimes harmful and not where the real energy of philosophy
should be
great.
So, uh let's wrap up the interview here then uh just before we go and by the way,
I'm also leaving a link in the description box
to your book Lydia on Lydia Maria Child.
Uh and apart from the book,
would you like to tell people where they can find you and your work on the internet?
Yes, thank you. I do have a website which is just Lydia Moland dot com.
And I am also on Twitter.
I think that's Lydia underscore Moland
and I have maybe two things on Instagram.
So I'm not, uh I'm not, never been a big social media person.
I'm getting my dipping my toes in a little bit, but
um Twitter is where I post the most and I do try to keep the website updated.
So people are more interested in in any of my writing.
Um All of my writing is listed on the website
and what I'm working on now is um findable on Twitter.
Ok, great.
So, Doctor Molan,
thank you very much for your time and it's been a real pleasure to talk to you.
Likewise. Thanks for your very insightful and detailed questions.
I really enjoyed it.
Hi guys. Thank you. For watching this interview until the end.
If you liked it, please do not forget to like it, share, comment
and subscribe.
And if you like more generally, what I'm doing, please consider support
the show on Patreon or paypal. You
have all of the links in the description of this interview.
This show is brought to you by en lights learning and development done differently.
Check their website
at
alights dot com.
I would also like to give a huge thank you to my main patrons and paypal supporters
per
Larson Jerry Mueller and Frederick Sunda
Bernards,
all
of
election
and
Weser, Adam Castle Matthew Whitting
Whitting Bear.
No
wolf, Tim Hoy,
Eric,
Alania, John Connors, Philip Forrest, Connelly, Robert Winde
Ruin. Nai
Zoup, Mark Nevs
Colin Holbrook,
Simon Columbus, Phil Kor
Michael Stormer,
Samuel Andreev
for
the
S Alexander Dan
Bauer Fergal
Ken
Hall,
her
OG
Michel
Jonathan.
Lebron
Jars
and
the
Samuel K
Eric Heins, Mark Smith,
Jan
Wera
Amal
Sran David
Sloan Wilson Yasa,
Des
Roma
Roach Diego
JP
Dr
Man, NCO
Bar.
We
and Pao
Assy
Naw
Guy Madison Gary GH.
Some of the
Adrian
Yin Nick Golden Paul talent in Ju
Bar
was Julian Price Edward Hall
Eden Bronner, Douglas Fry Franca
Bertolotti Gabriel Pan
Cortez,
Lelis
Scott Zachary Fish, Tim Duffy,
Sonny Smith, John
Wiesman,
Martin
Aland, Daniel Friedman, William Buckner, Paul George Arnold Luke Lo
A
Georges
the
often
Chris Williamson, Peter
Oren
David Williams, the
Costa
Anton Erickson Charles Murray,
Alex.
Shaw
and Murray Martinez
Chevalier,
Bangalore
atheists, Larry Daley Junior, Holt Eric B.
Starry Michael Bailey. Then Sperber, Robert Grassy
Rough the
RP MD.
Ior
Jeff mcmahon,
Jake Zul Barnabas Radix,
Mark Campbell, Richard Bowen
Thomas the Dauber
Luke
Ni
Andre story, Manuel Oliveira,
Kimberly Johnson and Benjamin Gilbert. A
special thanks to my producers is our web gem Frank Luca,
Tom Weam
Bernard
Ni
Ortiz Dixon
Benedict Mueller,
Vege,
Gli Thomas Trumble,
Catherine and Patrick
Tobin,
John Carlo Montenegro, Robert Lewis and
Al Nick Ortiz. And to my executive producers, Matthew Lavender,
Serge
Adrian and Bogdan Kut.
Thank you for all.