Hello everybody. Welcome to a new episode of the Center.
I'm your host as always Ricardo
Loops. And today I'm joined by Doctor James mccann.
He's Professor Emeritus of History at Boston University.
His research and
teaching interests include agricultural and ecological history of Africa,
Ethiopia,
and the Horn of Africa field research methods in African studies,
the Agroecology of tropical disease and the history of
food slash cuisine in Africa and the Atlantic world.
And today we are going to focus mostly on his book, Maize and Grace,
a History of Africa's Encounter with the new world crop.
So, Doctor mccann, welcome to the show. It's a huge pleasure to everyone.
Thank you for your invitation.
So, uh let's start, I guess at the beginning. So
uh we're going to talk about maize here today.
Where did maize originate from?
Maize is a new world crop that was
um
domesticated by
peoples in Mesoamerica.
And it's difficult, we don't know the exact
the first example of something we would call maize in the common term.
But there are examples of,
of um
archaeological evidence of forgive the bat cave where
they found something that looks a bit like maize
that has is on a,
on the ear with a, with a cob.
Um
And the evolution is the experimentation by local farmers.
We don't know
men and women both were involved probably.
But we don't really know that in Mesoamerica,
but the characteristics that were evolved over time
was farmer selection of certain characteristics they wanted to
have available in their own diets and their own food.
And maize is remarkable and it's spread internationally. That's why my interest in
the arrival of maize and its propagation in Africa.
It it's about farmer
household, local knowledge
only to some degree about elite a applications.
So it's the earliest history we don't really know for sure. The spread
me America
into
North America and as far as New England.
And for example, this is an exa example of a New England flint
and
eight rows
and it's not something commercially viable,
but it represents the kind of movement of,
of, of Mays into new environments.
This other example here you see
this looks like what Columbus would have brought with him.
He brought Mays back from the Caribbean,
a Caribbean red
flint, which is this one
to Europe and he sent it to his friends
in different places in Germany and Italy and Spain.
And it began to be experimented with and eventually was
taken over by farmers themselves who were the key innovators
both in Africa and in Europe.
When May spread as this popular crop that
had certain characteristics that were overwhelmingly popular with farmers
as they sought to
both be commercial but also to feed their local populations.
And what are some of those characteristics?
What are the most distinct traits of mace
maize is one, it is wind pollinated
in another. It's not pollinated by insects
or by um
by other means.
And on the maize plant, you have both male and female parts of the plant plant.
So it can self pollinate.
But for the most part, the wind moves the pollen
between fields and between plants.
So you get automatically a mix, genetic mixing
that gives you a final result of texture
color
and the characters
characteristics of the plant itself.
So it has this characteristic that farmers have, have,
have the ability to control it
by by hand moving the column.
Um so that they have characteristics that they favor
whether it's color or texture
or for example, how long it stores?
Uh some varieties of maize do not store very long at all,
you have to consume them or they go bad,
other ones will last longer. So farmers are making these choices over generations.
What the end result is? You find
the difference between these two.
I would say it's all about the farmer choices.
Another lead scientist, the farmer choices at the early level
and
the popularity of it as it spread around the world was because
it was controllable along with other new world. Um additions like capsicum pepper.
We can't recognize world cuisines without recognizing
the contribution of pepper capsicum.
Uh In
Indian,
Indian
Ethiopia, all varieties of taste
that we value coming from those new world exchanges
with new world. Yeah.
And uh what are some of the ways maize differs from other uh common crops?
Well, as I said,
the wind pollination factor is something that farmers have to learn to control
all the way to Monsanto. Suing farmers for
the pollen being carried by the wind across fields in Iowa
um or or elsewhere where the control of the pollen is
the key issue about how do you make it commercially viable.
Um
But the the difference when something like wheat,
wheat is wheat is self pollinating,
it doesn't,
the pollen does not move more than a few microns from different parts of the plant.
Rice is is self pollinating.
Uh So maize dis distinctive and it is wind pollinated, not insect pollinated
and that makes a huge difference. But farmers understood this pretty quickly
when any place where we see where maize has become adapted as a ma a major crop,
you see that farmers are adjusting their own knowledge systems
to the characteristics of maize. Maize is
hermaphrodite.
It represents both genders on the same club, but it also is
uh
I guess morally and and unquestionably about sharing sexual
engagements,
right?
And so, I mean,
we're also going to talk about how maize spread across the globe and specifically
uh in Africa.
Uh but what are,
are there specific ecological conditions where
maize produces high higher yields,
where it grows, it grows and is farmed the best?
Well, of course, that's a key characteristic.
And when
maize came from,
you know, directly, for example, from, from the
Atlantic trade with Brazil
and the trade, the Atlantic trade of course has is a complex interaction of sugar
and human labor, forced labor, you know,
slaves um going across and carrying maize as a potential crop brought into
the African case into West Africa, later into Southern Africa.
But also up the Nile
and into the Indian Ocean world where
the word the the Kiswahili
word
for
maize is
Muindi.
It's from India.
It doesn't come, didn't come from India.
But the the understanding, the popular understanding of where this thing came from
became the name.
If we look at the name for maize in different cultures, different languages.
We learned a lot about people's perceptions of that crop.
Um
In, in Malawi, for example, the word the word for, for maize, it means
um
from our ancestors, even though it came fairly late into place like Malawi,
we replaced sorghum.
Sorghum is not as productive as maize and, and farmers at each location,
whether it's tropical, subtropical um
or
somewhat um
affected by the amount of moisture available by rainfall by, by climate
farmers adjusted to that.
So you see the varieties of maize in all over the world
ad adapted
and again, not so much like recent times by corporations
who are, who are attempting to make maize science.
And that's the sort of dominant the farmers made
this choice every year when they selected their seeds,
they would, they would
choose some of the, some of the Mazier
for seed and some for consumption.
And the seed represented their sense of what
they identified is the characteristics they wanted.
And that includes the maize plant as forage, for animals.
So for example, in Italy,
the the the the the fact that the farm that the peasant farmers were able to
use the maize plant,
not just the the the ear,
but the plant itself to feed their cattle meant that they could keep the cattle in
the barns on their farm and not send them into the mountains in the winter.
And what they get from that is distinctive kinds of
products of the animals were eating the maize such as Parmesan,
such as Gorgonzola, the cheeses, Italians, Italy is so well known for
is part of the product of maize
is at the core feeding of the animals.
So they can be kept in the barns and fed over the course of the winter.
And thus ST storing the the milk
in the form of cheese.
So it's not that uh maize uh only
uh I mean grows well or produces a
good yield, good yields in specific climates.
I mean different kinds of maize have been adapted to
different sorts of uh climates and environments.
-- Yeah. With
-- the restrictions on maize, within the constraints
that farmers would respect would would um
develop is maize is is vulnerable to drought
moisture sensitive.
So if you, if you have a drought prone area, either seasonally
or within a year, you have to realize that maize is vulnerable to,
to moisture, to moisture uh availability.
The other way, maize tends does not store as long as other
crops, millets store for a very long time. Ethiopian crop
tiff
will, will store for years.
Maze, you get four months,
maybe maximum six months but unlikely. So you've got to eat it, move it,
preserve it somehow.
So it has those constraints on maze.
And so that's why you don't see maze as a domino c
everywhere.
OK.
Uh And when it comes, uh we've,
you've already mentioned some of that but when it
comes how and why it spread across the globe
apart from the trades
you've already mentioned,
were there any specific, for example,
political or economic reasons for it to become so widespread?
Uh
uh
Well, yes, one, it's, here's an example and this is not from the Africa work I did,
but the work I've done in Italy
where the key crop for the
veto.
Venice was an empire,
an empire of trade. But
they, the, the, the Venetian patricians,
the rich folks in Venice itself told the farmers on the terra
firma of
who they controlled that. You will pay your taxes and wheat.
And the farmer said wheat doesn't work well here in northern northern Italy,
wheat works in southern Italy and elsewhere.
So we want to start
paying our taxes in maize.
And at first, the patricians in Venice said,
no, we want wheat and we control you.
So the battle eventually was won by the peasants
in the terra firma.
And
because of the, the, the the plague and other kinds of situations,
they won the day and were allowed to pay their taxes in maize.
And of course, maize then becomes the basis for the diet in northern Italy of polenta
rather than pasta is an importation from Southern Italy.
And the same thing happens where maize is introduced in
uh in Africa where fa farmers find it help help
important to adapt maize as their fundamental crop.
But one of the liabilities of maize is it has
insufficient amino acids.
So you have the
pro from
palabra
is disease that you find
especially in agricultural societies
in
Southern
the American South, in
Italy
and any and in southern Africa, any place you have a dominance of maize in the diet
that came as part of,
of maize being
a really popular crop for farmers to grow
is Pella
is a skin disease
and you find it places where the diet becomes too dependent on maize.
But you don't find that in Mid
America
because in
Mesoamerica,
they process maize
using lies
and change the chemistry so that you get a complete uh
amino acid and complete protein by having a maize based diet.
It has to do with processing. How do you process the maze?
But they didn't do that
in um
in other places, Italy, Africa, the southern us
where Pella
becomes a serious problem
until it's understood that you have to complete the proteins by,
by research in the early 20th century.
And when exactly did maize get to Africa?
Well, we don't, of course, completely know,
but we can look at um
places early on, we begin to get adaptation.
For example, a na uh the names given to maize
you find in places in Nigeria
or West Africa
that the the words for maize tell us something.
The the um
the
Akan in
Ghana, uh
the word for, for,
for maize means something from the foreigners
in Ethiopia. Then one of the words for a maze was
Yar
Maila.
In other words, the sor
go from across the ocean,
it looks maize looks like.
So, so sorghum or Sorghum looks like maize when it's growing
early on.
But that the factor of people recognizing saying it's the so
them from across the sea.
And now when you go to to the place of within Ethiopia,
I work, it's just called
Mahila,
which just means Sorghum,
it's not Sorghum.
But people understand that the word tells you
people's perceptions of when this arrived.
Uh So exact dates
by the
time the Portuguese arrive in Ethiopia,
they're finding some maize there and they tell us what they're growing.
And
you can see the maize has already arrived.
But we don't have a clear historical record
because that's something takes place in the
basic level of human subsistence and doesn't
make it into the historical sources quite as clearly as it does later on.
And how does maize tie to Africa's Green Revolution?
Well, the Green Revolution originally
was done with rice for South Asia.
So, so for India, South Asia
and so that revolution was about doing short, short
that you have to have,
you have to have water and you have to have fertilizer and you get a huge growth in
food production
in South Asia
for Africa.
The the the attempt has been to say yes, maize is going to be for Africa
like rice was for South Asia
and that's done by has been done
by corporations by USA ID International Organizations.
Um
The key center for research on maize is in Mexico City
when I visited there.
Uh I was taken to uh there was Ethiopian there
who I
got,
I work in Ethiopia. So we became
friends. He took me to a rural site outside of Mexico City.
Uh
and they were growing their maize
seed for which was going to
be introduced to Ethiopia.
Uh So the international nature of the research going on now the Green Revolution,
the idea was maize can be the center point of that for Africa,
but with the problems that maze has about stability and about incomplete proteins.
And so what he this Ethiopian
scientist was doing,
I'm developing a new variety
with complete
um
proteins.
So it would have to be identified having a market value,
you pay more for those seeds to have complete proteins.
And this this
uh type of maize though was also introduced elsewhere in Africa
is part of what people hoped would be a green rev
kind of green revolution. And it has done that
the improvement in the the yield of the maize,
you improve maize is substantial to
um 68 tons per hectare
compared to two tons per hectare in local varieties.
So that is Africa was has been seen as the key to that
in many ways. It is
although
for example,
Ethiopian restaurants are very popular in around the world but in in the US
and in in Europe
and you will not find maize even though it's the number one crop in Ethiopia,
you will not find maize on the diet of
Ethiopia, the menu of Ethiopian restaurants
because it's not traditionally their ideal
food,
the food of poverty.
Um you can buy ears of maize on the street, roasted maize on the street,
very inexpensive.
But as a as a fund fundamental part of diet
problematic.
And why is it that uh when it comes to Africa, people decided on maize?
I mean, why wasn't it
some other crop.
Well, they have, you can, you can look at each individual situation.
The place I work in Ethiopia, they had a full
maize came very late. It was there as a garden crop,
early
yielding.
It's the first crop of the year.
You have it in your, your household garden.
Um,
you get the first milky stage, you can eat milky stage maize or wait,
wait till it dries and then process it.
But it's the first crop you're going to get.
Um
But there, there they had other crops,
they had death in wheat and barley.
And it was a very, very diversified cropping system. The farmers understood well
in other places, places in Southern Africa, for example,
it arrived, it replaced Sorghum
because it was much more productive. And the African farmers
all over Southern Africa said this thing will give us a yield quickly
and it is a food that we can adapt into our diet.
So sorghum has almost disappeared.
And maize is the crop that has many different varieties
in all the countries of Southern Africa. All different names.
Basically, it's what Americans would call, call grits
or Italians would call polenta.
Uh So maze in its various forms, ref reflects the the
choice of farmers to say this thing gives an early yield.
But the new varieties, the green revolution varieties yield much later
and you don't eat them at the m milky stage. At the green stage.
You have, you have to wait and dry them and then process them.
So it feeds into the industrialization of of mills
that began to change the way that the market
affected.
What kind of maize farmers were growing.
And the government would say, ok, you may, may grow
only this kind of maize because we cannot sell colored maize.
B
maize drops out of the market
because the international market say we want white maize.
And if yellow maize is grown, yellow maize is useful for poultry
who likes white yolks and their eggs,
the yellow comes from the beta
carotene in the yellow maize.
Hm
So you have these adaptations where the Millers are saying we want this
kind of maize because that's the one we can sell into international markets.
And so you have it for Africa. Virtually all of the African maize is white
in the US, maize is for livestock
and you want your, your the fat of your livestock to be kind of a little bit yellow.
So the the yellow maize is dominant in North America
and in Europe too, white maize is still there.
You can buy polenta, either white or red, depending on your taste.
What you're eating the polenta with,
with, with fish
or with uh with, with the tomato sauce, et cetera. So these are consumer preferences
that reflect the larger market preferences of the kind
of maize that farmers are going to be growing
to produce commercially for the market.
So uh politics and economics also certainly play a big
role in the adoption and spread of maize across Africa.
Right?
Yes.
So if you look at a place like Zimbabwe,
which did fantastic research on maize development,
the law system
eventually through the 20th century said, OK, you may not grow
maize which is not white.
Uh because white is the international market and we're producing
some of the best hybrid maize developed through research
came out not out of the North America,
out of Rhodesia, Southern Rhodesia, which became Zimbabwe.
Because the the, the,
the maize, the scientists there, the white, the white Rhodesian scientists
developed a incredibly productive uh
variety. But for that variety of, of really
um
productive maze in terms of, of the of the economic perspective
that you had to have just the right soils,
just the right moisture,
just the right seasonal conditions.
And of course, the white population in Southern Rhodesia controlled those things.
And the the black farmers were not given access to this new variety.
These new varieties
incredibly productive is from a scientific point of view, economic point of view.
But you also founded. This is a story I got when I was doing work, work in Zimbabwe,
one of those scientists
showed me a chart he made, he said, chart showed, wait a second.
Why is suddenly
this this production going up?
But we're not,
we're not charting.
He said in his own handwriting, he wrote in this little chart from the 19 sixties.
He showed me this chart
when I interviewed him,
he wrote African farmers.
In other words, African farmers had found the, the, the new crop,
the new variety and were using it
and adapting it in their own terms. Even though the government was
trying to suppress
their, their role in production of, of, of maize.
Very, very, very political economic,
in a fascinating way,
which is what led me into
and what led me into you didn't ask this question, but I'll answer it anyway.
How did I begin to understand
and,
and want to explore more of the role of maize
because I grew up with maize fields all around me as a kid.
I grew up in Illinois
and Illinois is a big maize producing area.
But when I was interviewing farmers in Ethiopia after the famine,
uh there was a socialist government in
place that was trying to control farmer activities
and farmers were growing their different varieties of crops.
And then suddenly
when I said, OK, what did you go last year, the year before that?
It's a year before that.
They were saying,
well, this is the maize, maize, maize, maize.
Really? I said maize is drought
is drought um
affected.
Um it, it it is
not the best nutrition in the world, it doesn't fit your normal diet.
Why are you doing this?
And so I began to understand it's because the
government is saying we don't care what you grow
as long as you pay in these other crops.
And they said that maize was safe because the government wouldn't
take it from him.
It was a political decision
that,
that affected what farmers did,
right? Uh And uh I mean, uh
going along the uh that line of what uh I would also like
to ask you a little bit about the particular case of South Africa,
which you have done some work on.
Uh you mentioned science there for example.
And I asked you about politics, but in the particular case of South Africa,
uh in what ways did politics, science and race intermingle there?
Well, for Southern Africa, we you know the politics,
we know of the the arrival of Europeans
in the 17th century and then spread from the cape
into colonial settings that were originally
the the arrival of uh Dutch later on the the the British Empire incorporated that
but the basic population
still was
agricultural.
Um And they of course had needs for the mines.
So the Southern African economies were about gold first,
sorry, diamonds first, then gold
and that became the diamond.
So what do you need? You need labor?
Mhm And when the labor is the black population
which needs to be fed
and the the mine owners were having to determine
what do we feed our mine workers to keep them
healthy enough to work
and maize became
the key crop for them. Uh
And the the word
Milly. Milly pop is a South African word for
polenta or for the basic maize, which comes from the Portuguese Mili.
So merely was not maize, but word came to include maize
from the original Portuguese.
And so you have this phenomenon of the mind economy, creating
a sense of what is
what is good food.
Um
And eventually the population came to define their full bellies
is the feeling you get
when you've eaten a big batch of maize.
And when that becomes a kind of a cultural norm of what feeling full is
um
maize becomes that key ingredient.
So the the miners also went back to their family farms when they worked,
headed out of the mines
and they began to grow maize
as down the crop.
And that was women doing the work back home where men were the miners earning wages.
And therefore
the the core diet became maze because it was low labor, lower labor.
Somebody I did mention
maze takes less labor, you can broadcast it.
Um You don't have to do it by role, et cetera.
Uh So its characteristics meant it could be
adapted on small farms in which women's labor
was the key issue.
So Southern Africa, it was about mining,
the economy and eventually became the accepted
um
diet
was maize was the core of any meal.
Yes, there was sorghum a little bit here and there. You can still buy some Sorghum in
South African. Uh gro
groceries.
But for the most part, the basic diet is
maize,
white maze.
Mhm.
Right.
And do we know if uh maize has had uh any impact on the biodiversity of Africa?
Well, in some ways,
it's a negative effect because the farmer
incentives with political context in many cases
is maize is the crop that's
really yielding. It gives a very good yield for small farmers and you go to,
you know, 6 to 8 tons per hectare of the new varieties.
So farmers are seeking both the commercial value of that to
to send to the the cities
but also it is very, very attractive is the local diet.
Um
So
the biodiversity
pushing maize as as USA ID does with the Agra,
the the this big development program
based upon maize is the primary crop.
Uh
So you have corporations Mon
Monsanto
and of course May's production,
Monsanto is now owned by
by year.
So the big maize producers are all owned by drug companies
by chemical companies.
Dupont owned all of those, those early developers of of maize in North America
in Europe are all owned by now. Chemical drug companies, Dupont Bayer
um
go down the line. So it
it becomes a corporate crop and farmers are are dealing with markets
and their own food supply depending on where you are in Africa.
Maize is not the dominant crop in every part of Africa.
It is in, it is in southern Africa.
It is in Kenya, Tanzania. Ugali
is essentially grits
polenta. But for, for East Africa
and that's
I had a friend, a Ugandan friend
who came to Ethiopia
and she was dying to have ugali in her diet because she's from Uganda and for her food,
met maize.
At that point, Ethiopian restaurant, Ethiopian
national diet did not really include maize
for the
middle and upper class.
So, Mays has his fun role, role. It's not a friend of biodiversity.
Mhm
And uh a related question,
do we know what impact uh the introduction of
maize had on African people's nutrition and health.
Well, I mentioned
pra
too much dependent on maize but maize has its place because it yields early
depending on the variety you're growing.
You can be can be the first thing that comes as the first crop
you have. We have often Af African cultures have celebrations of the first crop.
The the new year begins. The first thing you can get is maize
because you can eat it the milky stage as we eat with
with uh we haven't mentioned there are five varieties of maize,
one of which is sweet corn,
uh which is the one you eat at the milky stage.
It's wonderful, delicious. Um
Something in the fall when the first maze comes in,
you wanna have um sweet corn.
There's also popcorn, also dent corn, also flint corn.
These are both flint corns
which has the characters are scoring longer
uh which is a good thing, but they may take longer to mature and you're not,
you're not consuming them at the early stage.
So the the
the role of maize in the diet differs on which kind of cuisines you're talking about
which parts of Africa, Africa, of course, is a wonderfully diverse place,
linguistically, culturally,
in terms of diet
and maize plays an important part in a number of different African diets.
Mhm.
So for the second part of the interview, let's say,
I would like to ask you a few more
general questions not specifically related to maize itself.
So
uh particularly when I asked you about Southern
Africa and also earlier in the interview,
you mentioned a little bit of it,
uh we talked about colonialism. So
uh what would you say was the role played by
colonialism when it comes to spreading crops across the globe?
And uh how was the adoption of different crops influenced by it?
Well, it depends on the situation. We have an example of Ethiopia where there was not
formal colonialism. The Italian period was only a few years.
So the adaptation was done essentially by farmers themselves,
taking advantage of what is available to them in terms
of their own strategies of cropping across a year and feeding
their community with a little bit of commercials, selling of, of grains.
But also the household level.
When you go to a place like Southern Africa
or or
so Southern Africa, you have a large arrival of the European population
who are originally Dutch and then English
and then some Portuguese and different, different groups arrive there.
Europeans who control things
who are interested in feeding their labor
and feeding themselves. So you have in South Africa. So
a wonderful
um
tradition now of wine
because some of the early migrants out of Europe
were Huguenots.
The huguenots were escaping France because they were
oppressed by the Cat Catholic majority there.
And they began importing
uh vineyards
and that became now today, some of the best places to go and on wine tours in the world.
In my experience, South Africa is fantastic.
Um
And that links to the minefields needed labor.
The certain minefield, the vineyards needed labor and those laborers were eating
increasingly maize
getting back to maze
but it was
and some
places there was not a European population in East Africa, Kenya
a little bit Tanzania.
You had European populations that were affecting what farmers were doing
because they're expected that farmers would grow crops consumed by Europeans.
Uh West Africa,
the conditions of malaria,
something else I work on malaria meant that Europeans
and large populations did not populate West Africa,
they would tend to populate as in,
in um in India
hill stations that were
fear from malaria. So Europeans would con control those spaces
and so the population was allowed to keep
um
local varieties of foodstuffs. So for example, in West Africa,
you had the possibility of,
of uh maize could be there as a first crop if you're clearing your forest.
But the, the crops you really want to have in there are yam
cassava,
another manio,
another new world crop. Uh If you, you know bubble tea.
Uh yes,
the bubbles are maniac. A
casa.
We
were
OK.
Uh
So you have these mixes
sometimes called the Colombian exchange of crops coming from
the old new world to the old world.
I call it the I
call it not the exchange,
but the circulation
because the food crops along with peoples are
circulating and bringing their preferred foods with them.
So in West Africa, you have forest crops,
yams, they're, they're grown in the, in the, in the, in
the forest floor.
Uh Maize is there for the first crop but then people want to get into yams
and, and cassava
and other kinds of crops taken from the forest, the biodiversity of the forest.
So all that's changing, of course as cities grow.
But the colonial effect is greatest in some places where
there could be new neo Europe such as southern Africa,
Kenya.
But where there's factions of disease, the African population had resistance to
uh
the Europeans would tend to avoid those areas, control them for pro
production of food and for mining, et cetera.
But uh
maize there was, it's,
it's
interest came from farmers themselves.
But also because Europeans were happy to have those workers under,
under colonial rule fed
and the maze then became a key part of that process of nutrition.
Mhm.
So uh in historical scholarship, one approach that people have is to look at the
causal relationship between climate and history. Uh What do you think of it?
Climate is fundamental to history,
climate about seasonality. What is the annual cycle of, of
availability of moisture?
Uh Disease is also sea seasonal affected by climate by issues of climate.
It's the thing I'm working on now is sort of the more fundamental issue about water,
water, its presence, its absence, its movement,
it's movement through the seasons.
And this is
deeply within
the
issue of climate change, climate change,
velvet of water.
But of course, just look at today's stuff in, in Ukraine. But
what do you do when you want to defeat your enemy?
This is what the Germans did in Italy in World War Two.
They said we're gonna stop the allied invasion in Italy
by flooding the farmers' fields because then
that will encourage malaria which will affect
the invading army. In this case, the British American uh
invasion of Italy.
And that was a specific military plan,
what's going on now, even though we're not quite identifying the source of it.
This is what the Russians are doing.
They said we're going to blow up this dam and we're gonna flood this entire area
to
impede the movement of, of, of military activity
and this gets back to
the seasons in which empires within Africa, within Ethiopia. For example,
the the the armies moved only during the dry season.
If you move during the wet season, then the areas with malarial.
Uh so the seasonality of wind moisture is available is a big deal militarily
in terms of the production of food.
In terms of,
you know, if you, if you look at people who are traveling, describing
events in Africa or the conditions in Africa, Europeans writing down what they're,
what they're encountering,
they only traveled in the dry season.
They're only giving a partial view of what they're seeing
because they wouldn't go during the wet season
because it's one, it's muddy two, it's malarial
and the local merchants and,
and uh moving around are only doing their movement during that seasonality.
The seasons change, different parts of Africa,
but
it's that seasonal change and the, the issue of climate change,
which is now having major effects,
right?
Uh So I would like to ask you one last question slash topic. So,
uh of course, when it comes to history,
um I would like to ask you,
what do you think of approaches by people like Jared Diamond when
it comes to explaining why certain societies became more successful than others
and what we could call or at least some people call uh geographical determinism.
Well, that's always been a factor of how much is, are the conditions deterministic
and Jared Diamond lays out an argument.
That's interesting. To challenge
and it's good that it's there.
And it's, it's, it's an attempt at universal explanation of
human movement, human
political economic domination
based around on environmental issues to some degree. That's true.
Um
And I think that that any consideration of politics or of economic change
or of interaction between different kinds of political systems
um has its foundations, environmental issue in environmental issues.
The fact that Europeans
coming to Africa or even to North America or to, to the new world.
It's about the movement of knowledge.
Part of that Colombian circulation I mentioned was the arrival in
Latin America
of people who knew how to deal with
couple of climates.
The people, the the the selection of who is that most valued as
labor
out of the slave trade, going to the to the Carolinas in the US
because
the ones who are most valued came from Santa Gambia. They knew how to grow rice
and the the plantation owners. And so in, in um
in the Carolinas
were stayed in their, their uplands
and in areas that were not so much so affected by malaria or other diseases
and their, their African slaves were allowed to
move into swampy areas because they knew how to grow.
Um
love
rima rice.
They were adapting the environment, they knew,
they knew how to deal with health, knew how to deal with
production.
And so the knowledge that moved into the new world
also was a key part of this whole exchange
and
politics got into who controlled who but also
adaptation to environmental issues.
If you want to understand
the geography of Ethiopia
is a, is a place that's a place I work. Most,
you know, look at
climate seasonality
and you see that people would move in and out of areas that were affected by malaria
or where they could grow one crop or another crop and
then harvest it and get back to a safer area.
Big factor
and you a diamond is helpful to have that, that
um
that perspective
that is
environmental determinism,
but they will have nuance by local areas.
And that's the beautiful part of doing the,
doing the work and working with different people in different places.
Mhm.
So, yeah.
Uh I mean, I've also asked you about that because of course,
a big part of Jared Diamond's argument is based on
uh crops also, of course domesticated animals in certain specific latitudes
in the
world.
Uh And uh since of course,
our interview has been focused so much on maize
and we touched on some other crops as well.
Uh I was wondering, I mean, to what extent you would think
um
the factors that Jared Diamond points to
uh I, I mean, what uh how much of a role do you think they would play in
human history?
Well, I would add to Jared Diamond as,
as a um kind of marker of environmental determinism
with a reasonable coherent
and somewhat persuasive argument. But look at Alfred Crosby
who coined the term the Columbian exchange
that I modified to publicly of the interaction.
Um It
is
is that uh
Alfred Crosby talks about the the
biological imperialism
because the the arrival in the new world of cattle
and pigs,
right? And chickens
and part of this global circulation transforms
the the physical environment.
When you release
hogs into the environment, they are extremely good at going feral
and they, they,
they change the physical world they live in and humans are both either hunting them
or trying to domesticate them or
the the animals and the plants, of course, maize being a big one of
globalization,
but this is also true of other, other crops
and other kinds of animals. Um
you know, goats, sheep, cattle,
horses,
all of these things that transform
the worlds they they move to and the adaptation of local populations quickly to
the horse. For example,
you know, native Americans in North America adaptations of the horse,
suddenly they become mobile,
suddenly they, they're able to hunt in different ways.
Suddenly they're able to, to to expand their own local local
control over different com competing groups
in new, in new ways. So
the
the Alfred Crosby approach to this, which has been adapted by people,
scholars from,
from all over the world are incorporating these
ideas and and playing them out in local areas
that makes sense for them.
But Jared Diamond
more popular is, is something to read.
Uh It's kind of New York Times best seller list.
But the Alfred Crosby stuff is also
uh to me uh
very good.
And the colleagues I work with who are specialists
when I, when I go someplace, it's not that I know things
others don't know.
But I absorb as his historian,
I'm absorbing the knowledge and interacting with my colleagues,
whether it's in Ghana,
we were talking about the
introduction of maize or in Ethiopia where we're
driving through the countryside and I'm saying,
what's going on there?
We're walking through the countryside. And I'm always asking questions
because they have the knowledge that I've been trying to interpret for a larger
uh audience as an academic, as a historian.
So these things are very, very global,
it helps to have people kind of tweaking the narrative
by publishing books like Jared Diamond.
But it's not that we say gee he's got it. Right.
Um
He's after all, you know, his original background,
he's a gastroenterologist. Mhm.
Right.
And we trust doctors to a degree. Yes.
Yeah. Right.
So uh Doctor mccann, uh I'm leaving a link to your book Maze And Grace,
a History of Africa's encounter with the new World Cup crop
in the description box of the interview.
Uh Would you like to mention any places on
the internet where people can find your work?
Well, I think the internet being what it is, you can, you can do that.
Um What I'm getting now, I just was at Oxford University Press asked me
to write a chapter
on malaria in Africa.
And malaria in Africa came from my own work with, again, with colleagues
um who work on malaria in Africa and elsewhere.
But um people I got malaria when I was doing field work in Africa
uh in, in Ethiopia,
you know, an area where the maize stuff was going on.
And I didn't ask go malaria.
But suddenly I had 100 and five degree fever and had to
go back out of my my rural area five hours by mule
to get to the nearest road to the nearest light bulb.
Oh my God.
And so malaria became an interest and
the maze. Malaria connection is one chapter of of um maize and grace.
And so male malaria is where I I appear on the internet.
I'm constantly getting notes saying you've been cited by these 100 times.
I said really
I'm not doing
and it's, it's mainly now about the medical malaria stuff
that links to the maze. All these things are linked.
Um
And now
back to the North Fundament
of water
in which I'm doing a plenary panel for a international meeting in Finland
next year.
And that is to draw people together around
what is the meaning of water?
Meanings of water
as something physical
is something psychological is something
cultural
and water takes us to all kinds of ways
that people signify their sainthood if they're in a,
in a, uh
religious religious setting.
Um,
and for example, in the 88, the 18 fifties, this
short story,
the British traveler in Ethiopia
came down with fever
and it's called
eu, he understood this as I have a fever. What do I do?
He's riding around the countryside with people and they said,
what you need to do is stand in this tree and we're gonna dump water on your head
and this will deal with your fever.
He said, well, first of all, it knocked him off, his horse,
knocked him senseless
and he felt slightly better at the end of this ordeal.
At
the same time,
there's someone in Malvern England who's going through a water therapy treatment,
somewhat, somewhat similar
and that person was Charles Darwin.
So water is this, this,
this universal, of course, it's universal,
but the nuances and local cultures and local
material versus belief systems
is the thing that I'm working on now. And you find examples of that
all over the world
where suddenly cli that links to climate change.
Very interesting.
So, Doctor mccann, uh thank you so much for taking the time to come on the show.
It's been a real pleasure to talk to you
too.
Say
no
or the
equivalent of the Italian.
Yeah. In this case, uh it would be bo
part
here. It's still the afternoons. OK?
Time change, time change. So
thank you very much Ricardo.
Very interesting. You're, you're uh
you're a good, you're a good interviewer.
Thank you.
Hi guys. Thank you for watching this interview. Until the end.
If you liked it, please do not forget to
like it, share, comment
and subscribe.
And if you like more generally what I'm doing, please consider support
the show on Patreon or paypal.
You have all of the links in the description of this interview.
This show is brought to you by En Lights learning and development.
Done differently. Check their website
at
alights dot com.
I would also like to give a huge thank you to my main patrons and paypal supporters
per
Larson, Jerry Mueller and Frederick Sunda
Bernards
O
of
Election
and
Viser Adam
Castle Matthew Whit
Whitting Bear,
no
wolf, Tim Hollis, Eric Alania
John Connors, Philip Forrest, Connelly, Robert Winde,
Nai
Zoup, Mark Nevs
Colin Holbrook, Simon Columbus Phil,
Governor Michael Stormer
Samuel Andreev
for
the
Alexander Dan
Bauer, Fergal
Ken
Hall,
her
og
Michel
Jonathan
lebron
Jars
and
the
Samuel K,
Eric Heins, Mark Smith,
Jan
We
Amal
S Franz David
Sloan Wilson Yasa
Des
Roma
Roach
Diego,
Jannik Punter,
Da
Man
Charlotte Bli
Nicole Barbar
Wam and Pao
Assy
Naw
Guy Madison, Gary GH,
some of the
Adrian
Yin Nick Golden Paul talent in Ju
Bar
was Julian Price Edward Hall,
Eden Bronner, Douglas Fry Franca
Bertolotti, Gabriel Pan
Cortez
Lelis
Scott Zachary Fish, Tim Duffy,
Sonny Smith, John
Wiesman,
Martin
Aland, Daniel Friedman, William Buck. Paul George Arnold Luke Lo
A
Georges
the
offense,
Chris Williamson, Peter
Oren
David Williams the
Costa
Anton Erickson Charles Murray,
Alex
Shaw
and Murray Martinez
Chevalier,
Bangalore
atheists Larry Daley Junior, Holt Eric B.
Starry Michael Bailey then Sperber Robert Grassy
Rough the
RP MD.
Ior
Jeff mcmahon,
Jake Zul Barnabas Radix,
Mark Campbell, Richard Bowen
Thomas the Dubner,
Luke
Ni
and Greece story,
Manuel Oliveira, Kimberly Johnson and Benjamin Gilbert. A
special thanks to my producers, these our web gem Frank Luca Stan.
Tom Weam
Bernard
ni
Ortiz Dixon Benedict Mueller
Vege,
Gli Thomas Trumble,
Catherine and Patrick
Tobin
John
Carlo Montenegro, Robert Lewis and
Al Nick Ortiz. And to my executive producers, Matthew Lavender, Serge
Adrian and Bogdan Kut.
Thank you for all.